<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A survey of the world in ten books / by Barten Holyday ...</title>
            <author>Holyday, Barten, 1593-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2533</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280325</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58688</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 188:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A survey of the world in ten books / by Barten Holyday ...</title>
                  <author>Holyday, Barten, 1593-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Will. Hall for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maxims.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SURVEY OF THE WORLD. IN <hi>TEN BOOKS</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>BARTEN HOLYDAY</hi> D. D.  And Archdeacon of OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> —</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>Will. Hall,</hi> for the <hi>Authour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno MDCLXI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The Worthily Honour'd, the Vertuous and Learned <hi>Sr. RICHARD BROWN,</hi> Knight and Baronet, one of the Clerkes of his <hi>MAJESTIE'S</hi> Moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sr.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Remembrance of Just Delight de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; which as it is an acknowledg'd Truth in Nature; ſo eſpecially in the nature of knowledge. This at this time of Joy and Happineſſe for our Returne to theſe bleſſings, under our greateſt bleſſing, our moſt gratious Soveraigne, aptly prompts to a Repetition of thoſe Studies, to which the Love and Prudence of your Eminent Father promoted your Youth and my Induſtry about fourty years ſince, in your Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Inſtitution. The Improvement whereof as your Wiſdome has ſhowed in additions of Perſevering Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, weighty Employment and Nineteen Years Abſence from your dear Country: So in the Importunity of the late warres and opinions, ſome addition, I have made of After-ſtudies in the defence of Religion and Arts. With a neceſſary variety therefore from the ſingularities of the Divine Power and Wiſdome, I heere preſent the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er of Providence, in ſome things ſtrange, in All war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, by teſtimony of Men famous among Heathens
<pb facs="tcp:58688:3"/>and Chriſtians. Which diligence may bee to ſome a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for Choiſe and Cenſure; to Others no uncourteou<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Recollection of their Owne Thoughts. And as they were a Summer's recreations of my Age, caſt thus into the Faſhion of Ancient Memorials; ſo I intend them not as a Laborious Summe of knowledge; but only, as in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Pleaſure of a garden, as ſome more; pleaſing flowers cropp'd for the Complement and Enchridion <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Poſy: which by the Novelty may laſt a Day, and by the Art of Friendſhip, may, as Friendſhip ſhould, outla<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the vanity of the Flower. Yet as this pleaſes by Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the ſeeming Neglect renewing the delight, I but preſent, not obirude, to the leaſure of Your great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, reſpectfully remaining.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Noble Sr. The Glad Obſerver Of Your Choiſe Accompliſhments And Eminent Merits,</hi> BARTEN HOLYDAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:3"/>
            <head>To the Studious Reader.</head>
            <l>AS weary travelour that climbes a Hill,</l>
            <l>Lookes back, ſitts down, and oft, if hand have ſkill,</l>
            <l>Landſkippes the Vale with pencil; placing here</l>
            <l>Medow, there Arable, here Foreſt, there</l>
            <l>A Grove, a City, or a Silver-ſtreame,</l>
            <l>As offring to yield beauty to his Scheme;</l>
            <l>Then decks it for the Gallery, and Views</l>
            <l>If th' Eye and Phanſy count it Pleaſing News:</l>
            <l>So now my Thoughts and Hopes, that long have climb'd</l>
            <l>Learning's Aſcents, by which True Art's ſublim'd,</l>
            <l>Turne, Reſt, and their owne wandrings View. Here Light</l>
            <l>They ſee, by which they ſee; there deepeſt Night,</l>
            <l>The World's New <hi>Chaös:</hi> here a tinſell'd Sky,</l>
            <l>That does with beauty pleaſe and poſe the Eye;</l>
            <l>There Earth, Beaſt, Fowle, Myſtical Man, whoſe braine,</l>
            <l>A leſſe World, would the greater world containe,</l>
            <l>Theſe, if by Nature's Herald, Art, well plac'd,</l>
            <l>Preſent Nature and Art by Union grac'd.</l>
            <l>To view which, no new <hi>Alpes</hi> wee need, whoſe height</l>
            <l>Shows <hi>Europe</hi>'s dreſs, which Thence may 't Pleaſe, or Fright?</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:4"/>
            <l>Wee need no <hi>Ararat</hi> to ſhow <hi>Aſian</hi> Glory,</l>
            <l>It ſelfe having Ark'd-up rich <hi>Aſia</hi>'s ſtory.</l>
            <l>No <hi>Atlas</hi> need wee, <hi>Africa</hi>'s proud eye,</l>
            <l>The Myſteries of its Deſerts to diſcry.</l>
            <l>The New world's <hi>Andes</hi> wee can wiſely ſpare:</l>
            <l>The proſpect there, but not quick death, is rare.</l>
            <l>Wee need no <hi>Tenariffa,</hi> which does ſhoote</l>
            <l>So high, my eye J'de lend it, not my foot.</l>
            <l>No cunning mountaine need wee, whence the Devil</l>
            <l>Would ſhow the whole world's Glory, not the Evil:</l>
            <l>Fear'd hee 't would ſpoile his Bribe? But here below</l>
            <l>From Art, not Mountaine, Truth enough wee ſhow.</l>
            <l>If then thy Eye venters to bee ſo kind,</l>
            <l>Scone View the Long View of a Searching Mind.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, BARTEN HOLYDAY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:4"/>
            <head>The ARGUMENTS Of The Several Books.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. OF Inanimate Creatures.</item>
               <item>2. Of Living Creatures.</item>
               <item>3. Of Nations.</item>
               <item>4. Of Languages and Arts.</item>
               <item>5. Of Philoſophers and Hiſtorians.</item>
               <item>6. Of Phyſitians.</item>
               <item>7. Of Lawiers.</item>
               <item>8. Of Kings and other Worthies.</item>
               <item>9. Of Polititians.</item>
               <item>10. Of Divines.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOK I. OF</hi> Inanimate Creatures.</head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58688:5"/>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>THe <hi>Heav'n</hi> is Arch; Therefore it ſelfe Suſtaines:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Earth</hi> is Center; Therefore So Remaines:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>World's</hi> a Priſon; no man can get out:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et th' Atheiſt ſtorme then; 't is Heav'n round about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eav'n</hi> is the Silke-worme's Spheare: what Art did ſpinne it</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oes at its pleaſure chooſe to dwell within it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow bleſt was <hi>Steph'n,</hi> whoſe eje <hi>Heav'n</hi> did permi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſee, who does at th' Father's right hand ſit!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Was <hi>Paul</hi> more happy at the <hi>Third Heav'n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſight</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r more Tormented to Delay Delight?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Who firſt <hi>Mov'd</hi> Heav'n, Philoſopher's halfe-ſkill</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquir'd: 'T was Hee, that made the Sunne ſtand ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> weight from the <hi>Ninth Spheare</hi> Ninety yeares ſpends,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y two hundred miles an howr, e're't quite <hi>Deſcends!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Man <hi>Aſcended</hi> ſtill tow'rd the <hi>High'ſt</hi> ſpheare,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight thouſand yeares hee'd ſpend, e're hee were There!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he white and yelke are cloſures in a ſhell:</l>
               <l>Art thus makes Orbes kindly in Orbes to dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Many</hi> Heav'ns wee thinke there are below</l>
               <l>The High'ſt: to This by Thoſe faire ſtepps wee goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58688:6"/>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Low'ſt Aſcents</hi> in Heav'n have each their Light:</l>
               <l>The Next is Fill'd with ſtarres; No point is Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Starry</hi> Heav'n, which Divine power ſo paints,</l>
               <l>In Figure ſhews th' Aſſembly of the Saints.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>13.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saturne,</hi> next the fix'd ſtarres, wiſe death may preach:</l>
               <l>Thoughts muſt bee ſober, that think Heav'n to reach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> was in Fiction Joy: but in the Skie</l>
               <l>'Tis the next ſtep to <hi>Saturne's</hi> Gravitic.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>15.</head>
               <l>A Heav'nly <hi>Mars,</hi> what is't, but a ſtour hand,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Dragon, in Saint <hi>Michael's</hi> Band?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sunne</hi> is a Great Light to all eyes free:</l>
               <l>And yet Heav'n's Greateſt Light wee cannot ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17.</head>
               <l>The Hurry of the <hi>Sunne</hi> in his Owne Spheare,</l>
               <l>That meaſures Thriſe five Miles each Minute Heere!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>18.</head>
               <l>Seemes not the <hi>Sunne,</hi> for <hi>Speed</hi> of courſe, to merit</l>
               <l>The name, not of a Body, but a Spirit?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Copernicus</hi> will have the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſtand ſtill,</l>
               <l>To ſcape doubts: Hee makes New! This is New skill!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20.</head>
               <l>Some New <hi>Astronomers</hi> in the <hi>Sunne</hi> find Spots:</l>
               <l>Heav'n was nere Curs'd: The Sunne's Light knows no Elot!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58688:6"/>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>21.</head>
               <l>Some find of late New ſtarres about the <hi>Sunne!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Needs hee more light? God's work with wiſdome's donne!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in Heav'n muſt needs bee Faire and Pure:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f it Invites, it mocks, the <hi>Epicure.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>23.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſercurie's</hi> Witt and Tongue doe plainly tell</l>
               <l>The Witt and Tongue find place in Heaven, us'd well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>24.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Moone</hi> is the World's Glaſſe, in which, 't were ſtrange,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f wee ſaw Hers, and ſaw not our Owne Change!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25.</head>
               <l>The learned <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> has the Journy meaſur'd</l>
               <l>Up to the <hi>Moone:</hi> ſure, wiſe men he has pleaſur'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26.</head>
               <l>News from the <hi>Moone;</hi> 't is told by very Fame,</l>
               <l>There's a ſtrange Man, from <hi>Adam</hi> that ne're came!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <head>27.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Galilie</hi> in the <hi>Moone</hi> finds yet more Change:</l>
               <l>The Man i' th' <hi>Moon,</hi> once Tale, ſeems Truth! That's ſtrange!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28.</head>
               <l>Traſfique to th' <hi>Moone!</hi> Is't done by art of Wing?</l>
               <l>To Aſcend, prov'd <hi>Chriſt</hi> God! what proves this New thing?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29.</head>
               <l>Who'll <hi>flie</hi> to Heaven, muſt ſtore of Vict' alls keepe!</l>
               <l>And ſometimes muſt at once both Flie and ſleepe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <head>30.</head>
               <l>Some think the <hi>Starres</hi> Holes, through which Heav'n ſends Light:</l>
               <l>Then into Heav'n might not aſcend Our night?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58688:7"/>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31.</head>
               <l>Some thinke the <hi>Earth</hi> a <hi>starre:</hi> then ſhould it Light</l>
               <l>Send forth abroad upon the Heav'n by Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Arabians</hi> will the <hi>Starres</hi> like Letters ſpell;</l>
               <l>But who did e're <hi>Demonſtrate</hi> what they tell?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <head>33.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Experience</hi> oft Pretends, not ſo True Art:</l>
               <l>That may miſtake; from Truth This does not ſtart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fore-knowledge</hi> is Divine; Man's Witt Ambitious:</l>
               <l>What's <hi>Hali, Nabod, Bonat, Alcabitius?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Goate-witted Man</hi> to climbe will venter, if</l>
               <l>Hee may; though hee hangs by th' claws againſt a cliffe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <head>36.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Art of ſtarres</hi> who knows, but Hee that made them?</l>
               <l>But Man's bold Gheſſe, to God's wrong, would invade them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37.</head>
               <l>To found an <hi>Art on Figurative Grounds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reaſon without true Art ſondly confounds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>38.</head>
               <l>What though, to worke on Earth, the <hi>Starres</hi> Indeavour;</l>
               <l>Since what's receiv'd is chang'd by the Receivour?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <head>39.</head>
               <l>What though the <hi>Starres</hi> with lower cauſes cloſe,</l>
               <l>If in Man's Actions Grace does Interpoſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Milky Way</hi> which does the Heaven imbrace,</l>
               <l>Shews, Men of Small Light may in Heaven find place;</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58688:7"/>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Milky Way</hi> muſt with the ſtarres bee rang'd:</l>
               <l>What's out of Heav'n continues not Unchang'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <head>42.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Light,</hi> what it is, does Senſe, nay Wit, well know?</l>
               <l>Light is ſcarce light enough, it ſelfe to ſhew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>43.</head>
               <l>The World's a picture; <hi>Light</hi> at firſt was hurld</l>
               <l>Upon't: Is it God's ſhadow in the world?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Fire</hi> next Heav'n's like zeale; but not ſo Cruel;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Burnes, yet not Devours: 't is its Own Fuel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <head>45.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Aire's</hi> Higheſt Region's Hot; Cold in the Middle;</l>
               <l>The Low'ſt by Reflexe Warme: See Nature's Riddle!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thunder</hi> preſents God's Majeſty to th' Eare;</l>
               <l>Which is the Gate of Faith and Holy Feare!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>47.</head>
               <l>When Heare and Cold, met in the ſame cloud, jolt;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Thunder's</hi> Sentence! Guilt's the Thunder-bolt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <head>48.</head>
               <l>When, on Mount <hi>Sinai, Thunders</hi> loud did roare,</l>
               <l>They ſhooke the Mount, and th' Holy Cloud they toare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49.</head>
               <l>One moſt ſtrange <hi>Meteor</hi> has it ſelfe renound,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sinai-Trumpet,</hi> which it ſelfe did ſound!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50.</head>
               <l>At the <hi>Last-Day,</hi> when all things down are hurl'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jehovah's</hi> Voice ſhall <hi>Trumpet</hi>-up the World!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:58688:8"/>
            <lg n="51">
               <head>51.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lightning</hi> Appeares firſt: Thunder's firſt: The Eie</l>
               <l>Of Conſcience ſees Guilt, before Judgment's Nigh!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lightning,</hi> the Mother Sav'd, the Child within</l>
               <l>Has kill'd! The Soule ſav'd, Conſcience ſo kills Sinne!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <head>53.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Comet,</hi> is't the Carbuncle of Sinne,</l>
               <l>Maſs'd-up from th' Earth and Hell, whence 't did begin?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <head>54.</head>
               <l>How at a <hi>Comet</hi> ev'ry one does ſtare?</l>
               <l>When many, who thus Gaze, worſe Comets are!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>55.</head>
               <l>Who <hi>Many Sunnes ſees,</hi> ſees not his Abuſe;</l>
               <l>Unleſſe of his Miſtake hee makes more Uſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56.</head>
               <l>Clammy Smoakes Fir'd and <hi>Falling ſtarres</hi> ſome call:</l>
               <l>Their phanſie erres; Truth from their witt does fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <head>57.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Fooliſh Fire</hi> oft, that by night does move,</l>
               <l>Does by Miſtake or Feare, Focles make or prove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <head>58.</head>
               <l>What Bluſtring, Hott, Thick Aire's This? 'Tis the <hi>Wind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faint Embleme yet of Man's more Troubleſome Mind!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="59">
               <head>59.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whirle Wind,</hi> th' art a Surprize! Nothing's like Thee</l>
               <l>But Rapture, from the Spirit of Propheſie!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <head>60.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Raine's</hi> Cloud Diſſolv'd: Thus from the Law, Sad Feares.</l>
               <l>By warmth of grace, deſcend in fruitfull Teares!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58688:8"/>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Red, Green, Blew, which ſometimes paint the Aire,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uilt, Pardon, Heav'n, the <hi>Raine-bow</hi> does declare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Raine-bow</hi> to the Sunne yields due reſpect:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>race, the Soule's beauty, does to God Reflect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="63">
               <head>63.</head>
               <l>When Heav'n rain'd <hi>Clouds,</hi> and did Our World confound;</l>
               <l>The Aire ranne Chanel, and All Seas were Drown'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome make <hi>Dutch Schuarts</hi> Founder of Gunnes and Shot:</l>
               <l>The Volly of <hi>Haile</hi> and th' <hi>Amorites</hi> they forgot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65.</head>
               <l>Th' Earth through great Heat, Cold, Wind, <hi>Dew</hi> oft does lacke:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Luſt, Deſpaire and Rage, Grace is kept-backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="66">
               <head>66.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hoare-Froſt,</hi> a Dew congeal'd, on high Hills ne're</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s found: Preſumption unacquainted is with Feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <head>67.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Snow</hi> is a Cloud, Light, but congeal'd: Grace Join'd</l>
               <l>With Doubt, may knowledge, yet leſſe Comfort, find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="68">
               <head>68.</head>
               <l>At the laſt Day ſhall the Saints <hi>Meteors</hi> bee?</l>
               <l>Their Earth ſublim'd ſhall yet from Change bee Free!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="69">
               <head>69.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sea</hi> is the Earth of Water: The ſunne draines</l>
               <l>What's pure ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om Groſſe: Sea, that is, Salt, remaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="70">
               <head>70.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sea</hi> is ſalt; Salt's Wiſdome: That can reare</l>
               <l>The weight of ſhippe; This the world's burden beare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58688:9"/>
            <lg n="71">
               <head>71.</head>
               <l>It is the <hi>Moone's</hi> Increaſe, that ſwells the Ocean:</l>
               <l>'Tis the <hi>Firſt mover</hi> ſhews the <hi>Way</hi> o'th motion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="72">
               <head>72.</head>
               <l>Vanity does too oft man's large Mind fill:</l>
               <l>But the <hi>Firſt mover</hi> Guides th'obedient will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="73">
               <head>73.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>River</hi> is Time in Water: as it came,</l>
               <l>Still ſo it flowes; yet never is the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="74">
               <head>74.</head>
               <l>Some think th'Earth ſtarre: Indeed ſtarres ſend forth Beams.</l>
               <l>Wee'll call it Heav'n; the <hi>Springs</hi> ſo ſend forth ſtreams.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="75">
               <head>75.</head>
               <l>Shoot up an arrow, not farre off 'tis found:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moves</hi> th'<hi>Earth</hi> then ſwift enough, if it turnes round?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="76">
               <head>76.</head>
               <l>Shall not the <hi>Aire</hi> turne <hi>faster</hi> then the Earth?</l>
               <l>To think it moves not ſo, is't Truth, or Mirth?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="77">
               <head>77.</head>
               <l>Wonders we have on <hi>Earth;</hi> thus wee may know</l>
               <l>What things there are Above, by what's Below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="78">
               <head>78.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clay, Sand</hi> and <hi>Rocke,</hi> ſeem of a diff'rent birth:</l>
               <l>So men; ſome Stiffe, ſome Looſe, ſome Firme: All Earth!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="79">
               <head>79.</head>
               <l>Downe Picke-axe, to the Depth for <hi>Gold</hi> lets goe:</l>
               <l>Wee'll undermine <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u:</hi> Is'nt Heav'n Below?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="80">
               <head>80.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> Nature's Jugler's Many in One:</l>
               <l>Now it is Fix'd: Now 'tis Looſe: now 'tis Gone!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58688:9"/>
            <lg n="81">
               <head>81.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> Conſcience, play not Faſt and Looſe:</l>
               <l>Faſt will the Looſe bee, to it's Owne Abuſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="82">
               <head>82.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Marble,</hi> a ſtately Vanity, does ſhow,</l>
               <l>In Natur's A<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, Spots doe for Beauty goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="83">
               <head>83.</head>
               <l>Each Duſt <hi>Loadſtone</hi> has two points: 't will riſe</l>
               <l>To th' Loadſotone: Many at once may fright our eyes!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="84">
               <head>84.</head>
               <l>Why ſhould the world the <hi>Diamond</hi> ſo commend?</l>
               <l>This Conſtant is: the World's a Crumbling friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="85">
               <head>85.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Emerald's</hi> the Ey's Favorite: wee doe</l>
               <l>In One find the Object and Spectacle too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="86">
               <head>86.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Ruby</hi> is an Earth, and yet a Fire:</l>
               <l>A Holy Man! What Earth to Heav'n comes Nigher?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="87">
               <head>87.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Margarite's</hi> compos'd of Heavenly Dew:</l>
               <l>Heav'n is the <hi>Pearle,</hi> that is prepar'd for Few!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="88">
               <head>88.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cedar</hi> the Dead from Putreſaction keepes:</l>
               <l>The juſt more ſafely in <hi>Chriſt's merits</hi> ſleepes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="89">
               <head>89.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Oake</hi> beares Fruite, though Bloſſome it beares none:</l>
               <l>The juſt beares fruite, though of it is not knowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="90">
               <head>90.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Olive</hi> loves Hot ground, not fat, nor leane:</l>
               <l>Grace is the Juſt Man's Joy, in ſtate though Meane.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58688:10"/>
            <lg n="91">
               <head>91.</head>
               <l>The Serpent ſhunnes the Odour of the <hi>Vine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Venom'd Soule flies from the Sacred Wine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="92">
               <head>92.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Laurell's</hi> a perpetual Green: wee may</l>
               <l>See Grace thus flouriſh. Grace is its owne <hi>Bay.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="93">
               <head>93.</head>
               <l>By whom ſhall <hi>Cinnamon's</hi> praiſe bee fully Chanted?</l>
               <l>'Tis as Reſtorative, as Deſire Granted!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="94">
               <head>94.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Corne,</hi> the <hi>Graſſe,</hi> for Man, for Beaſt, renew:</l>
               <l>God teaches them to Feed and Teach us too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="95">
               <head>95.</head>
               <l>Courſe wonder, <hi>Garlicke!</hi> Begger's <hi>Galen!</hi> Wiſe</l>
               <l>Thy Clownes are: Noſe-coy fooles thy Wit Deſpiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="96">
               <head>96.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Pinke</hi> by Nature's ſo refin'd, wee dare</l>
               <l>Allmoſt to aske, whither't is Flow'r, or Aire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="97">
               <head>97.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Violet,</hi> the Flow'r of Courteſie, Delight</l>
               <l>Does yeild unto the Touch, Taſt, Smell and Sight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="98">
               <head>98.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Roſe</hi> is but the Flower of a Brier:</l>
               <l>The Good man has an <hi>Adam</hi> to his Sire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="99">
               <head>99.</head>
               <l>What's Beauty without Vertue, but the <hi>Lilie?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faire to the Eye; the ſent will quickly fill yee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="100">
               <head>100.</head>
               <l>To weed the <hi>Garden</hi> pleaſure prompts ſome Care:</l>
               <l>To weed the Mind, ſhall ſafety no time ſpare?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:10"/>
            <head>BOOK II. OF <hi>Living Creatures.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:11"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58688:11"/>
            <lg n="101">
               <head>101.</head>
               <l>WHo can Acres of <hi>Whale,</hi> in the Ocean See,</l>
               <l>And with's Owne wonder, not Aſtoniſh'd bee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="102">
               <head>102.</head>
               <l>To ſee Nine hundred foote of <hi>Whale,</hi> may make</l>
               <l>One thinke, Iland for Fiſh hee does miſtake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="103">
               <head>103.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Whale,</hi> a Live Sea, <hi>Jonah</hi> did incloſe:</l>
               <l>Were Night, Feare, Grave and Hell at once his foes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="104">
               <head>104.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jonah</hi> found Aire in water: though command</l>
               <l>Freedome he could not; did he not find Land?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="105">
               <head>105.</head>
               <l>Woder in Wonder doe the Sea-men note:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Whale's</hi> vaſt bulke has but a narrow throate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="106">
               <head>106.</head>
               <l>What's great <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that does turmoile</l>
               <l>Himſelfe ſo much in Wave, but Bone and Oile?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="107">
               <head>107.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oile</hi> makes the wool run in the Cards the better:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sathan's</hi> glibbe arts make Man to Grace more debter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="108">
               <head>108.</head>
               <l>Though the <hi>Whale's</hi> Bone finds uſe too much about us,</l>
               <l>Yet Grace and Wit keep the Devil and that without us.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="109">
               <head>109.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Whale's</hi> Mouth's a Portcullis, but Inverted?</l>
               <l>Th' under jaw's Teeth into Holes above inſerted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="110">
               <head>110.</head>
               <l>O Man take heed of Hell: if that once Swallow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leviathan</hi> does ſhew thee, what does follow!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58688:12"/>
            <lg n="111">
               <head>111.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Greene</hi>-Land Sea's the world: with happy Gale</l>
               <l>And Art of grace, lets maſter the Great <hi>Whale!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="112">
               <head>112.</head>
               <l>Out with your barrels, Sailours, the <hi>Whale's</hi> neere:</l>
               <l>Upon another point inſtantly ſteere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="113">
               <head>113.</head>
               <l>A <hi>black beaſt</hi> with ſquare head, fiery eyes, 't is Tradition,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſland</hi>-Seas ſhow: Is't Fiſh, or apparition!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="114">
               <head>114.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Cuttle</hi>-Fiſh with's Inke the Sea does ſtaine:</l>
               <l>His Witt's his Veile: A ſearch is then but vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="115">
               <head>115.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Rémora</hi> a ſhippe's courſe ſtopps ſome ſay:</l>
               <l>The Dev'l indeed our Chriſtian courſe would ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="116">
               <head>116.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Crampe</hi>-fiſh does the Fiſher catch: his hand</l>
               <l>Hee ſtupifies: Thus Craft 'gainſt Craft does band.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="117">
               <head>117.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Polonians</hi> to Revenge doe not more thronge,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Dolphins</hi> ſhoale it, if you doe them wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="118">
               <head>118.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Porpiſe,</hi> the Sea-<hi>Almanack,</hi> fore-ſhows</l>
               <l>A Storme: Hee's happy that worſe ſtormes fore-knows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="119">
               <head>119.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shrimp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Sea-<hi>Elixir.</hi> though thy Circle's ſmall,</l>
               <l>Thou art to man Food, Temperance, Life and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="120">
               <head>120.</head>
               <l>The Prince of Feaſts, the <hi>Sturgeon,</hi> does command</l>
               <l>The Ghueſts: Th' Obey, that think they underſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58688:12"/>
            <lg n="121">
               <head>121.</head>
               <l>The Dainty <hi>Salmon</hi> Courtier of the Seas,</l>
               <l>With Temperance is pleaſure; els Diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="122">
               <head>122.</head>
               <l>Why ſhould the backward <hi>Crabbe</hi> bee ſo aſham'd!</l>
               <l>They rather that Abuſe him ſhould bee Blam'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="123">
               <head>123.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lobster,</hi> the warmth of Age, is but Repaire;</l>
               <l>'Tis but Abus'd, when Us'd for prouder fare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="124">
               <head>124.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lamprey</hi> is Danger; ſtomach is but Coy;</l>
               <l>Pleas'd you may bee; you may your ſelfe Annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="125">
               <head>125.</head>
               <l>Nine times an <hi>Eele</hi> through a Cormorant has paſs'd.</l>
               <l>E're kild: A ſlipp'ry Sinner's caught at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="126">
               <head>126.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Seale,</hi> the <hi>Pike,</hi> the <hi>Perch,</hi> though fiſh, wee muſt</l>
               <l>For true repaire, call fleſh: 't were els Unjuſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="127">
               <head>127.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Gudgeon</hi> is the tender ſtomach's meat</l>
               <l>And Sauſe: of this the Rich and Poore may eat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="128">
               <head>128.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Trout</hi> repreſſes Choler: what is Coole.</l>
               <l>Hot, Moift, or Drie, in fare; ſhould bee our Schoole.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="129">
               <head>129.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fiſh</hi> ſpeake God's Love and Wiſdome, without Voice:</l>
               <l>All's not for All; but Some for All with Choiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="130">
               <head>130.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sharke,</hi> the <hi>Otter,</hi> Vexe the Sea and River:</l>
               <l>What Sanctuary can Man ſtill deliver?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58688:13"/>
            <lg n="131">
               <head>131.</head>
               <l>The Dying <hi>Moale,</hi> ſay ſome, Opens his eyes:</l>
               <l>The Rich, till 'tis too late, will not be wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="132">
               <head>132.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Worme</hi> Lives in his Grave: Doe what he can,</l>
               <l>He's but a worme. No muck-worme is a Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="133">
               <head>133.</head>
               <l>To Heav'n a Soule ſome Old Philoſophy gives:</l>
               <l>On Earth the <hi>Gloow-worme</hi> is a Starre, and Lives.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="134">
               <head>134.</head>
               <l>See the <hi>Ant's</hi> Mountaine! <hi>Babel's</hi> Tow'r againe?</l>
               <l>Heere's as much Bus'neſſe! Though't is not ſo Vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="135">
               <head>135.</head>
               <l>What Seeds th' <hi>Ant</hi> Stores, he Bites: what Grows, hee Looſe</l>
               <l>Scarce ſhall he grow, whom a Grand Politique Uſes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="136">
               <head>136.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Spider</hi> builds in Palaces; Her owne</l>
               <l>Is webbe: i' th' midſt whereof ſhee's Queen Alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="137">
               <head>137.</head>
               <l>To One man's peace, the <hi>Spider's</hi> Wiſdome ſhows,</l>
               <l>An Other man his peace oft wiſely Owes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="138">
               <head>138.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Flies</hi> oft remov'd returne: Doe they want Feare,</l>
               <l>Or Shame, or Memory? Flies are ev'ry where.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="139">
               <head>139.</head>
               <l>A dried <hi>Toad</hi> layd nigh th' Heart, ſtays blood: wee have</l>
               <l>Sinne, which if layd to Heart, the Soule may ſave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="140">
               <head>140.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Flea,</hi> that feeds on Duſt and Blood, not long</l>
               <l>Triumphs; Hee's Snapp'd: Such is the end of Wrong!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58688:13"/>
            <lg n="141">
               <head>141.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Gnat</hi> is the poore man's Revenge: Hee brings</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mall ſtrength; yet makes great noiſe, and ſhrewdly ſtings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="142">
               <head>142.</head>
               <l>What in the flow'r is found moſt pure and Sweet,</l>
               <l>That only for his Combe the <hi>Bee</hi> thinks meet!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="143">
               <head>143.</head>
               <l>The Monarch <hi>Bee,</hi> when feeble, by the reſt</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s carried: So Jrrev'rence they deteſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="144">
               <head>144.</head>
               <l>Whole pits with <hi>Hony</hi> in <hi>Lithuania</hi> flow:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uge Beares are Choak'd in it; Pleaſure's a Foe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="145">
               <head>145.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Silke-worme's</hi> its owne wonder, without Loome</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t does provide it ſelfe a ſilken roome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="146">
               <head>146.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Silke-worme's</hi> Nature's Poet, who excels</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n phanſie, in whoſe Court with Art hee dwels.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="147">
               <head>147.</head>
               <l>See how the <hi>Eagle</hi> mounts tow'rds Heav'n: Hee's gone</l>
               <l>Quire out of ſight; Right Embleme of Saint <hi>John!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="148">
               <head>148.</head>
               <l>Brave bird of Thunder! <hi>Capaneus</hi> was Fable:</l>
               <l>'Tis th' <hi>Eagle</hi> Dares breaſt Lightning, and ſeemes Able.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="149">
               <head>149.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eagle</hi> and Lightning met, in juſt account,</l>
               <l>May make us thinke, wee ſee <hi>Eliah</hi> mount.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="150">
               <head>150.</head>
               <l>In th' <hi>Eagle's</hi> Eye ſee th' Eye of Juſtice, fierce</l>
               <l>Both ſeeme, and, what they view, they deepely pierce.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58688:14"/>
            <lg n="151">
               <head>151.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Eagle's</hi> Thigh does the Lion's thigh Out-waigh!</l>
               <l>Is's not a Bird of an Imperial Sway?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="152">
               <head>152.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Eagle</hi> to the Sunne preſents his yong:</l>
               <l>Is't Bold? Hee Owns't: Aoe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'t Turne? Away't is flung.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="153">
               <head>153.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mount,</hi> O my <hi>Soule,</hi> and to thy maker bring</l>
               <l>Thy loſtieſt Thoughts, his Gift, with Soaring Wing!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="154">
               <head>154.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſcend,</hi> My <hi>Soule,</hi> ſometimes, but to repaire</l>
               <l>Strength for New Flight into Diſcov'ring Aire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="155">
               <head>155.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Eagle</hi> caſts his Bill, and becomes New:</l>
               <l>Oh, may my Soule find but a Change as true!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="156">
               <head>156.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Vultur</hi> will draw blood from his Owne thigh,</l>
               <l>If hee wants Prey! <hi>Herodian</hi> Cruelty!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="157">
               <head>157.</head>
               <l>Man, haſt thou Grace? Th' haſt Sinne! See, 'tis but Meet</l>
               <l>Not only the <hi>Swan's</hi> Feathers, but his Feet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="158">
               <head>158.</head>
               <l>Pride can not ſee it ſelfe by Mid-day-light: l</l>
               <l>The <hi>Peacocke's</hi> Taile is Fartheſt from his Sight!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="159">
               <head>159.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Parrot</hi> learn'd the <hi>Creed:</hi> may not ſuch, greeve,</l>
               <l>As can not ſay't, or can not it Beleeve?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="160">
               <head>160.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Nightingale's</hi> a Quire, no Single Note:</l>
               <l>O Various pow'r of God in One ſmall Throate!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58688:14"/>
            <lg n="161">
               <head>161.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Cuckow's</hi> but Two Notes: what Artiſt tells</l>
               <l>The Cauſe? Or why the Nightingale excels?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="162">
               <head>162.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Cuckow's</hi> Halſe an Owle; Hee flies Man's fight:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Owle,</hi> a double Cuckow, flies by Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="163">
               <head>163.</head>
               <l>Wonder it ſees, where ſo e're the Eye does Rowle:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Batt</hi> is the Aire-Mouſe; The Night's his Hole.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="164">
               <head>164.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Swallow's</hi> a Quicke Arrow, that may ſhow</l>
               <l>With what an Inſtant Swif<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe Life does flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="165">
               <head>165.</head>
               <l>Though the <hi>Cocke's</hi> Muſique from his Vigour bee,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an is left pos'd: The full cauſe can hee ſee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="166">
               <head>166.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeſe</hi> Sav'd <hi>Rome's Capitol,</hi> the <hi>Cocke</hi> Saint <hi>Peter:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o a wiſe Mind his Muſique's ſure the ſweeter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="167">
               <head>167.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Yong the <hi>Pidgeon</hi> firſt with Salt-earth feeds:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe Education thus a wiſe man breeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="168">
               <head>168.</head>
               <l>With what a Roare of Fury <hi>Lions</hi> rage?</l>
               <l>'Tis Halfe a Fright, to ſee the Lions Cage!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="169">
               <head>169.</head>
               <l>That doe wee talke of Wild beaſts more then One?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> is a Wilderneſſe Alone!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="170">
               <head>170.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> vex'd, with taile ſtrikes th' Earth; Next blow</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates his Owne Back: The Laſt Confounds his Foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58688:15"/>
            <lg n="171">
               <head>171.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Ly<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian Lion</hi> eates Man, Woman, Child:</l>
               <l>Eates Him; Then Them: His Hunger's wiſely Mild!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="172">
               <head>172.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Leopard's</hi> ſo ſtrong, ſo Quicke, ſo Fierce;</l>
               <l>As if, whiles Nam'd, hee'd Leape too in the Verſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="173">
               <head>173.</head>
               <l>As from the <hi>Tiger</hi> ſwift and fierce wee'd runne:</l>
               <l>With greater Care our greateſt Foe lets ſhunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="174">
               <head>174.</head>
               <l>Cruell's the <hi>Beare,</hi> h' has yet but a weake head;</l>
               <l>A blow has kild him: by <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Death Sinne's Dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="175">
               <head>175.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Arabian</hi> Fox robbes Houſes, and ſteales Shooes:</l>
               <l>Our Foe would us ſpiritually ſo abuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="176">
               <head>176.</head>
               <l>The Rav'nous <hi>Wolfe</hi> will feed on Mice and Moles:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sathan</hi> does thus devoure darke Earthy ſoules!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="177">
               <head>177.</head>
               <l>O mocke of Pride! Man can not Change his Shape:</l>
               <l>Though, whiles unchang'd, hee is but like an <hi>Ape.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="178">
               <head>178.</head>
               <l>The ſhifting <hi>Heare</hi> wee pitty; ſcorne the <hi>Hart;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To flie when Arm'd, is but the Coward's part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="179">
               <head>179.</head>
               <l>The Sicke <hi>Hart</hi> eates a Snake, and ſo grows well:</l>
               <l>Repentance Digeſts Sinne, and Man ſcapes Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="180">
               <head>180.</head>
               <l>Much 't is the <hi>Afrique Camels</hi> Long can faſt:</l>
               <l>More, that they Inceſt Hate, admir'dly chaſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58688:15"/>
            <lg n="181">
               <head>181.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>normous Excellency! Th' <hi>Elephant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ſtrength, nor wit, nor words, ſome ſay, does want!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="182">
               <head>182.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the <hi>Elephant's</hi> Heart is found a mighty Bone:</l>
               <l>Inhappy Man, whoſe Heart is oft All ſtone!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="183">
               <head>183.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Aſſe</hi> for Burden, as the <hi>Horſe</hi> for Speed,</l>
               <l>God has giv'n Man, Man's Double helpe at need.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="184">
               <head>184.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Aegyptian</hi> thought the <hi>Dog</hi> a God! Hee might</l>
               <l>Take him a Friend: Hee's Safty or delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="185">
               <head>185.</head>
               <l>Glutton-<hi>Jew</hi> of all men was moſt croſs'd:</l>
               <l>The various dainties of the <hi>Hogge</hi> hee loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="186">
               <head>186.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Cow</hi> yields milke; the <hi>Sheepe</hi> cloths: both are good,</l>
               <l>Thus both Alive; and when Both Dead, th' are Food.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="187">
               <head>187.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Catt's</hi> Eye's Providence, It Sees by Night:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Guard of <hi>Angels</hi> yields both Joy and Might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="188">
               <head>188.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore Life to <hi>Man,</hi> then to the <hi>Crow</hi> God gives:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong lives the <hi>Crow: Man</hi> lives, and Dies, and Lives!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="189">
               <head>189.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an's <hi>Braine</hi> is Curds and Wonder! Truth this cleares:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>athuſhelah's</hi> was unchang'd nine hundred years!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="190">
               <head>190.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blood</hi> Circles from the Heart unto the Heart:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an's New <hi>America</hi> ſpeakes <hi>Harvie's</hi> Art!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58688:16"/>
            <lg n="191">
               <head>191.</head>
               <l>I' <hi>Wake</hi> and ſo new Live: a Night's Protection</l>
               <l>Is a new Wonder, whiles a Reſurrection.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="192">
               <head>192.</head>
               <l>I' <hi>Wake</hi> and too too ſoone my Thoughts begin</l>
               <l>To ſtray: Can Sleepe halfe-Reſcue us from Sinne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="193">
               <head>193.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sunne's</hi> up: yet My ſelfe and God moſt bright</l>
               <l>I can't ſee: J'me too Darke, and Hee's too Light!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="194">
               <head>194.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cloths,</hi> which Hide ſhame, ſhame us, ſinne they preſent:</l>
               <l>Wee're Cloth'd yet in the Grave, when Innocent!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="195">
               <head>195.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hand,</hi> waſh thy fellow; yet the waſhing's vaine:</l>
               <l>Wee are Sinne's Black-Moores, though wee waſh againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="196">
               <head>196.</head>
               <l>Let devout <hi>Prayer</hi> caſt me to the Ground:</l>
               <l>So ſhall I yet to Heaven bee Neerer found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="197">
               <head>197.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>What</hi> ſhall I <hi>Doe</hi> to day? I pray'd to ſhunne</l>
               <l>All Sinne; but, from my Prayer 'tis, I runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="198">
               <head>198.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hunger</hi> ſays, Feed: Feed? ſays Temperance;</l>
               <l>Through Food, Sloth, Sleepe and Luſt, Life's but a Dance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="199">
               <head>199.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Holy Book</hi> is my Receite; a Sure</l>
               <l>Cordial, a Pow'rful Trouble, and a Cure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="200">
               <head>200.</head>
               <l>Advance <hi>My Taſke,</hi> Thy Praiſe, Spirit Divine!</l>
               <l>I'le Slight the Aide then of Poëtique Wine!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:16"/>
            <head>BOOK III. OF <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:17"/>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58688:17"/>
            <lg n="201">
               <head>201.</head>
               <l>TIs <hi>Morning;</hi> therefore <hi>Night;</hi> This Order keepes</l>
               <l>The world: ſtill One Halfe wakes; the Other Sleepes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="202">
               <head>202.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow <hi>Nations</hi> fill the Earth, like Diff'rent Seeds!</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch Country unlike Men and Manners breeds!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="203">
               <head>203.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Spanjard's</hi> Sober, Wiſe, Conſtant, Devout;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Avarice, Pride, Luſt, Blood! Th' <hi>Indian</hi> cri'd out!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="204">
               <head>204.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine's</hi> the Third <hi>Indies;</hi> Spice and Gold it ſleights:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deeper Mines of Counſaile it delights.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="205">
               <head>205.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>French,</hi> wine of <hi>Orleans?</hi> Flame, Wounds, Scarres?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ates hee the Chronicle by Civil warres?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="206">
               <head>206.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h' <hi>Italian's</hi> the World's Gentleman; A Court!</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o which, Thrift, Witt, Luſt and Revenge reſort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="207">
               <head>207.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey erre, who <hi>Rome's Hills</hi> by the Old names call:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Vatican</hi> is now the <hi>Capitol.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="208">
               <head>208.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alie's</hi> Church is <hi>Rome; Naples</hi> the Court:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ononia</hi> the Great Schoole; <hi>Venice</hi> the Port.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="209">
               <head>209.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame does for wiſdome <hi>Venice</hi> highly reare:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Turke</hi> ſuſpects, their Wiſdome is Halfe Feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="210">
               <head>210.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ybaris</hi> once for Vice was the World's Blot:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he World's a ſtaine! <hi>Sybaris</hi> now's no Spot.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58688:18"/>
            <lg n="211">
               <head>211.</head>
               <l>When from the <hi>Alpes</hi> the <hi>Afrique</hi>-General</l>
               <l>View'd <hi>Italy,</hi> their Top was <hi>Hannibal.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="212">
               <head>212.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Britans,</hi> yee are ſtout men; bee alſo wiſe:</l>
               <l>They'd need bee ſo, on whom are all mens eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="213">
               <head>213.</head>
               <l>Faſhions and Propheſies are <hi>England's</hi> ſtaine:</l>
               <l>Lets not bee Mad too, though wee have been vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="214">
               <head>214.</head>
               <l>Bogges, Purgatory, Wolves and Eaſe, by Fame</l>
               <l>Are counted <hi>Ir'land's</hi> Earth, Miſtake, Curſe, Shame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="215">
               <head>215.</head>
               <l>Earthquake is ſcarce acquainted with <hi>Scotch</hi> Ground:</l>
               <l>Yet many Jolts of State have There been found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="216">
               <head>216.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Belgian's</hi> the World's Scout: Water's his Land:</l>
               <l>His Fleete's his Country; and his Art's his Hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="217">
               <head>217.</head>
               <l>The Portly <hi>Alman,</hi> if wine ſays not Nay,</l>
               <l>Beares his Head high, as if his head bare ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="218">
               <head>218.</head>
               <l>Of <hi>Daniſh</hi> kings <hi>Chriſtian's</hi> a Name and Riches,</l>
               <l>Could they make Chriſtians of their Norway-Witches.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="219">
               <head>219.</head>
               <l>Whom more then the Firſt <hi>Suede</hi> did Fame e're cloy?</l>
               <l>This made <hi>Lutzen</hi> more Griefe, then His Life Joy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="220">
               <head>220.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ruſſia</hi> is wilderneſs; the Man is Furre:</l>
               <l>Thatch is his Houſe; his Winter's One Long Murre.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58688:18"/>
            <lg n="221">
               <head>221.</head>
               <l>Againſt his Owne Foes the <hi>Polonian's</hi> bold:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gainſt Heav'n's has his Owne Winter been more Cold?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="222">
               <head>222.</head>
               <l>Can the <hi>Racovian</hi> thinke troubles can ceaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f with <hi>Socinus</hi> God's Foe hee's in peace?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="223">
               <head>223.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hungarie's</hi> king is alſo <hi>Damocles:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Right gives Throne; th' Impendent Sword no Eaſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="224">
               <head>224.</head>
               <l>Th' Old <hi>Greeke</hi> was Mirth and Wine; now wretched feares</l>
               <l>May make him drinke in Silence his own teares!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="225">
               <head>225.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Turke</hi> ſells Liberty! The <hi>Turke</hi> does prize it</l>
               <l>Though't's Above price! The pooreſt <hi>Gre<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke</hi> yet Buyes it!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="226">
               <head>226.</head>
               <l>The Owle, <hi>Athens</hi> held Sacred: ſure a ſoule</l>
               <l>Miſtake of phanſy! <hi>Athens</hi> was the Owle!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="227">
               <head>227.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Athenian</hi> Wit ſcorn'd to bee <hi>Paul's</hi> Witt's Debter:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt <hi>Paul</hi> n'ere grac'd th' <hi>Athenians</hi> with a Letter!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="228">
               <head>228.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Candie's</hi> the Chriſtian Weere: the Seas oft racke</l>
               <l>Amaine, from <hi>Helleſpont:</hi> yet oft rowle backe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="229">
               <head>229.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Turke's</hi> Mad to bee Mad: Hee's a Darke Mind:</l>
               <l>Which can no Heav'n, but his Owne Body, find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="230">
               <head>230.</head>
               <l>To <hi>Homer's</hi> Muſe, but firſt to its Owne ſhame</l>
               <l>And Ruine, <hi>Troy</hi> owes its Unhappy Fame!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58688:19"/>
            <lg n="231">
               <head>231.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> once thought to make <hi>Troy</hi> a New <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Byſanti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um</hi> got the Name; Hee got a Tombe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="232">
               <head>232.</head>
               <l>A ſtately Shrine the Dev'l at <hi>Epheſus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did raiſe: he would ſupply a Loſt Heav'n Thus!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="233">
               <head>233.</head>
               <l>Paradiſe o're <hi>Granada</hi> hangs; <hi>Spaine</hi> boaſts!</l>
               <l>But Heav'n Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaw, o're the <hi>Pathmian</hi> Coaſts!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="234">
               <head>234.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Iſrael Canaan</hi> left; <hi>Canaan</hi> became</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegypt:</hi> but <hi>Goſhen</hi> got <hi>Canaan's</hi> Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="235">
               <head>235.</head>
               <l>Old <hi>Salem</hi> Longer was, then broad; though Faire:</l>
               <l>But New <hi>Ieruſalem's</hi> a perfect Square.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="236">
               <head>236.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>God's Temple</hi> was Earth's Heav'n, yet Heaven he bow'd:</l>
               <l>Came downe, and dwelt in Myſtery and Cloud.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="237">
               <head>237.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arabia</hi> once was happy: Now what's Left,</l>
               <l>But Sottiſh <hi>Mecha,</hi> Wilderneſſe and Theft?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="238">
               <head>238.</head>
               <l>When God dwelt forty years midſt Rockes and Sand,</l>
               <l>Was not the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> a Holy Land?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="239">
               <head>239.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Babel</hi> was Nebuchadnezzar! at leaſt</l>
               <l>In pride! In Judgment too! 'Tis very Beaſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="240">
               <head>240.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Babel's</hi> proud walls, that were an Army, Now</l>
               <l>By turnes do to the <hi>Turke</hi> and Perſian bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58688:19"/>
            <lg n="241">
               <head>241.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> Dwells on Horſe-back: Surely Hee</l>
               <l>Was the Right Centaure in Old Poëtry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="242">
               <head>242.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Tartar,</hi> Nature's Heretique, Roaves in State:</l>
               <l>Hee's a Land-Planet; or, what ſome call Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="243">
               <head>243.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>India's</hi> the World's Faire: Gold, Spice, Gemmes, d' yee want<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>They're There; the Carrier too, the Elephant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="244">
               <head>244.</head>
               <l>With Silkes and phanſies th' <hi>Eaſt</hi> the world does fill:</l>
               <l>How farre wee faile to pleaſe but our Owne Will?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="245">
               <head>245.</head>
               <l>The <hi>China</hi>-Anchorets Wall'd-up did dwell;</l>
               <l>The Snaile was not more faithful to his ſhell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="246">
               <head>246.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Amboina's</hi> Spices doe the Body warme:</l>
               <l>But Got by violence doe the Soule more harme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="247">
               <head>247.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ormuz,</hi> Eye of the Sea, if thou 'dſt ſhine bright,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hine with a Chriſtian Chriſtalline, thou 'lt ſhine right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="248">
               <head>248.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aloes</hi> from <hi>Zocatrà</hi> who but procures</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Health? Bitter Repentance who Indures?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="249">
               <head>249.</head>
               <l>When God to <hi>Sheba</hi> wiſdome did unfold,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſent him its Firſt wiſdome, Spice and Gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="250">
               <head>250.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sheba</hi>-Queene, who mov'd by <hi>Solomon's</hi> fame,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame to bee wiſe, was wiſe before ſhee came.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58688:20"/>
            <lg n="251">
               <head>251.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Abiſſine</hi>-Child Baptis'd in Fire may ſtart:</l>
               <l>Growne Man, a fire hee muſt have in his Heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="252">
               <head>252.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mountaines</hi> o' th' <hi>Moone</hi> wee heare of; whoſe Foote's <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe Top is Heav'n! who'll then a fall There Vent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="253">
               <head>253.</head>
               <l>Earth in the Moon has <hi>Galilaeus</hi> found?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Mountaines</hi> of the <hi>Moone</hi> are ſurer ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="254">
               <head>254.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nilus</hi> is <hi>Aegypt's</hi> Almanack, prevailes</l>
               <l>To fore-tell ſtore; how s' ere the Starres-Man faile's.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="255">
               <head>255.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Aegypt's</hi> king God's word Tranſlated ſhoud,</l>
               <l>Sure thrice five Cubits then <hi>Nilus</hi> oreflow'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="256">
               <head>256.</head>
               <l>Vaſt and Full <hi>Cair,</hi> if Fame does not beguile us,</l>
               <l>Th' art Double-ſtor'd: Thy People is a <hi>Nilus!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="257">
               <head>257.</head>
               <l>Thy Founder, <hi>Alexandria,</hi> makes thee ſtory:</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is thy Greateſt glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="258">
               <head>258.</head>
               <l>Who thinks <hi>Cyréne</hi> Barren, his Witt's Groſſe:</l>
               <l>It brought forth <hi>Simon,</hi> who did beare Chriſt's Croſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="259">
               <head>259.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> did once each other feare:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Auſtin's Hipp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> conquerd both; 'tis Cleare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="260">
               <head>260.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Hannibal,</hi> bee 't ſet upon thy tombe:</l>
               <l>Treacherous <hi>Carthage</hi> was great <hi>Hannibal's Rome!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58688:20"/>
            <lg n="261">
               <head>261.</head>
               <l>Who thinkes <hi>Algier's</hi> Holy, ſurely beleeves</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Howſe of Pray'r's ſometimes a Denne of Theeves.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="262">
               <head>262.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oledo's</hi> prelate wonne <hi>Oràn</hi> to <hi>Spaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <hi>Chriſt:</hi> a Two-edg'd Sword's a Double gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="263">
               <head>263.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ez</hi> wonder is: a Building without Ground!</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſchees and Hoſpitals, where no Faith's found!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="264">
               <head>264.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ez</hi> obſerves <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Birth-day: Verſe does flow!</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall wee doe leſſe for <hi>Christ,</hi> who more doe Owe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="265">
               <head>265.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arocco's Tow'r</hi> three Globe of <hi>Gold,</hi> moſt faire</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Art and Weight, grace: 'Tis a Mine i' th' Aire!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="266">
               <head>266.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree <hi>Silver</hi>-Globes ſurmount <hi>Marocco's Spire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lmanſor's</hi> worth above them yet mounts Higher.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="267">
               <head>267.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>midia's</hi> ſand and wild Beaſt! Is ought worſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Mankind of the Country is the Curſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="268">
               <head>268.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> way to <hi>Atlas,</hi> you whom Luſt does pleaſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h' Aire cures, though not the Soule, the Ranke Diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="269">
               <head>269.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lia,</hi> thy Lions like Thy Sunne-beames rage:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unger and Flame more eaſy 't is to' ſwage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="270">
               <head>270.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abia</hi> once <hi>Christian</hi> was; ſure <hi>Arian too!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Rankeſt poiſon's There, that e're man knew.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58688:21"/>
            <lg n="271">
               <head>271.</head>
               <l>The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknowne Lands'</hi> i' th' <hi>South;</hi> your Mappe-men ſay:</l>
               <l>It is as well i' the Midſt of <hi>Africa.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="272">
               <head>272.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Congoant,</hi> when Heathen, made their Foe their Meat:</l>
               <l>Now no man, but their friend, by Faith they eate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="273">
               <head>273.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Angola</hi> Slaves, for gaine, once joint-meat ſold'</l>
               <l>Could Nature bee unnatural, though Bold?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="274">
               <head>274.</head>
               <l>Why are Some <hi>Negros?</hi> Did it firſt proceed</l>
               <l>From <hi>proper</hi> Situation? Now, from Breed?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="275">
               <head>275.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Guinean</hi> fires his houſe, when Warres begin!</l>
               <l>In Holy warfare could wee ſo leave Sinne!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="276">
               <head>276.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Canarie's</hi> grape was in the <hi>Portugall's</hi> power;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xerez</hi> in Spaine's: Has <hi>Spaine</hi> now Sweete and Sowre!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="277">
               <head>277.</head>
               <l>Had <hi>Teneriffa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> top by th' Arke been found,</l>
               <l>Would then the <hi>Babel</hi>-men have raiſd their ground?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="278">
               <head>278.</head>
               <l>Tow'rds <hi>Africa</hi> a Sea of Weeds wee have:</l>
               <l>Is't not the picture of the World in wave?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="279">
               <head>279.</head>
               <l>Stranger, would'ſt Die? Saint <hi>Thomas-Iland</hi> ſee:</l>
               <l>By Fifty, Nature's <hi>Jubily</hi> ſets thee free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="280">
               <head>280.</head>
               <l>On <hi>Good Hope's Cape</hi> ſeemes there a Paradice Spred!</l>
               <l>Fruit There Man eat; with raw guts Heere they're fed!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58688:21"/>
            <lg n="281">
               <head>281.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Wiſdome may diſcover; Speed and Way</l>
               <l>May make us thinke, <hi>Ophir</hi> was <hi>Sofalà.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="282">
               <head>282.</head>
               <l>Deſtroy the World's ſtore, and but <hi>Zeilan</hi> ſpare,</l>
               <l>May n't wee from Thence (D' yee doubt?) the World re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="283">
               <head>283.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eas Cement Lands: did then by th' Art of Boate</l>
               <l>Croſſe th' <hi>Anyan</hi> Ferry World to World firſt floate?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="284">
               <head>284.</head>
               <l>The South-Eaſt Ilands did New <hi>Guiny</hi> fill:</l>
               <l>Might they not teach <hi>Fogo</hi> Like Love and Skill?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="285">
               <head>285.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mayre's</hi> ſtraights and <hi>Magellan's Fogoans</hi> paſſe-over:</l>
               <l>Three times as farre from <hi>Calice</hi> 't is to <hi>Dover.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="286">
               <head>286.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Magellan</hi> Gyants doe like Canon, roare:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure then they need no Beacons on the ſhoare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="287">
               <head>287.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perù's</hi> a Land of promiſe: is 't ſo Holy?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Tempts; yet ſome, for Gold, find their owne Folly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="288">
               <head>288</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Potoſi</hi> Mines ſeeme <hi>Midas's</hi> Hell; a Hold</l>
               <l>For Dev'lls? what is digg'd-up is thought but Gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="289">
               <head>289.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n th' <hi>Andes</hi>-Hills, hee that Takes breath, does Looſe it;</l>
               <l>Cold breath of Death! To view two Seas, who 'd Chooſe it?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="205">
               <head>205.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Plate</hi>-Streame ſeem'd at firſt a Silver-Mine:</l>
               <l>But water there, not Silver, now does ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:58688:22"/>
            <lg n="291">
               <head>291.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Brazile</hi>-Cannibal is his Enimie's Grave!</l>
               <l>Two Reſurrections yet at laſt they 'll have.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="292">
               <head>292.</head>
               <l>Wee ſought <hi>Guiana</hi>-Gold out at the Line:</l>
               <l>Wee loſt a <hi>Raleigh,</hi> a farre richer Mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="293">
               <head>293.</head>
               <l>Cut <hi>Aegypt's Iſthmus</hi> South will ſome Seas goe?</l>
               <l>Cut <hi>Darien</hi>-Iſthmus th' Ocean Weſt will flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="294">
               <head>294.</head>
               <l>The Old World ſtill did ſee New <hi>Generations.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Men: but Our World does behold New <hi>Nations.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="295">
               <head>295.</head>
               <l>New <hi>Spaine, France, England,</hi> now Riſe in the Weſt:</l>
               <l>In our Sunne-Set they Riſe, if they prove Beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="296">
               <head>296.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mexico</hi> firſt was founded in a Lake:</l>
               <l>Was't not in Earth, Aire, Water, a Miſtake?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="297">
               <head>297.</head>
               <l>In Feather-worke the <hi>Mexican's</hi> ſo quaint;</l>
               <l>That Feather is the Creature and the Paint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="298">
               <head>298.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Card of the North-Seas was playd:</l>
               <l>To Mocke, not Guide, ſome thinke it firſt was layd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="299">
               <head>299.</head>
               <l>Diverſe a North-Weſt-Paſſage faine would find:</l>
               <l>The Wind's content; The Frozen Sea's Unkind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="300">
               <head>300.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>America's</hi> North's Triangle; South's a Heart:</l>
               <l>Bee th' Iſthmus Faith, from God can th' <hi>Indian</hi> ſtart?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:22"/>
            <head>BOOK IV. OF <hi>Languages and Arts.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:23"/>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:58688:23"/>
            <lg n="301">
               <head>301.</head>
               <l>WHat by an Angell's donne with Inſtant Thought,</l>
               <l>That by <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> in Man About is brought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="302">
               <head>302.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ightly to Underſtand is Happineſſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oore 't is, what's Underſtood, well to <hi>Expreſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="303">
               <head>303.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rammar</hi> does Guide the Tongue; <hi>Logique</hi> the Reaſon:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey witt-up Youth to Man in Nature's Seaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="304">
               <head>304.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>het'rique</hi> does Language grace: in Age 't is Youth:</l>
               <l>Tis not meere Shape; the Beauty 't is of Truth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="305">
               <head>305.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sceleton</hi> to th' Eye preſents each Bone;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith Truth, not pleaſure: Bare 't is, and Alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="306">
               <head>306.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Divine Wiſdome does <hi>Man's Frame</hi> preſent;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut cloths each part with Fleſh, its Ornament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="307">
               <head>307.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Mind formes <hi>Thoughts,</hi> Thoughts, <hi>Words:</hi> which undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Art's</hi> Choice Order, aptly may bee Guided.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="308">
               <head>308.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ature</hi> produces <hi>Art;</hi> by Helpe Divine</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Curious Worme extends his Silken Line.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="309">
               <head>309.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Eare is a great Critique; and can tell</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſound, if but an <hi>Accent</hi> falls not well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="310">
               <head>310.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Greeke</hi> ſlippe <hi>Caninius</hi> ſtraight would Smile:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anklin</hi> would ſay, that it does All quite ſpoile.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58688:24"/>
            <lg n="311">
               <head>311.</head>
               <l>Great Judges of <hi>Jöt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> count nor Litle,</l>
               <l>The errour of a Breathing, or a Tittle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="312">
               <head>312.</head>
               <l>Without your <hi>Art-Markes</hi> Language knows no Laws;</l>
               <l>The Wrinkles of the Knuckes have their Cauſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="313">
               <head>313.</head>
               <l>Heralds of <hi>Accents</hi> Books and Braines'doe Vexe,</l>
               <l>To Place the Grave, th' Acute, the Circumflexe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="314">
               <head>314.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stephanus</hi> is Great Treaſurer o' th' <hi>Greeke:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſo for Bread th' <hi>Aegyptians</hi> ſeeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="315">
               <head>315.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Athens</hi> for Choiſe phraſe was a Choiſe peece,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Budaeus</hi> 't was, that was the <hi>Greece</hi> of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="316">
               <head>316.</head>
               <l>Slips th' <hi>Hebrew</hi> Accent, <hi>Schindler</hi> ſtraight deſcries it:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maire</hi> too: but Curious <hi>Donat</hi> moſt defies it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="317">
               <head>317.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Weigangmeir</hi> Tables-up each point and Letter;</l>
               <l>It can not ſtirre: You 'll find it in its ſetter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="318">
               <head>318.</head>
               <l>Does <hi>Pagnine</hi> or <hi>Marinus</hi> Maſſe-up words?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hutter's</hi> or <hi>Schwenter's</hi> ſmall Cube all affords.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="319">
               <head>319.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kirſten</hi> and <hi>Raphelenge</hi> are th' <hi>Arabique</hi> Moone:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Erpen, Giggeius, Pococke</hi> are High Noone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="320">
               <head>320.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Megeſer Turkiſh</hi> ſhow; The <hi>Perſian, Greave:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What Tongue untaught doe ſome or other Leave?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58688:24"/>
            <lg n="321">
               <head>321.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Mithridate</hi> ſpake <hi>Dialects</hi> Twenty-too:</l>
               <l>With Halfe th' Art <hi>Nimrod</hi> had made more adoe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="322">
               <head>322.</head>
               <l>Your Throtling Tongues who would not ſcape? They're worſe</l>
               <l>Then Ignorance! To Learne then is the Curſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="323">
               <head>323.</head>
               <l>The Weſt-Tongues to the <hi>Latin,</hi> are but ſleight:</l>
               <l>They are but oblique Caſes from the Right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="324">
               <head>324.</head>
               <l>The Slipp'ry <hi>French,</hi> and Mouth-roof'd <hi>Spaniſh</hi> know</l>
               <l>No Mean: Th' <hi>Italian</hi> does more wiſely flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="325">
               <head>325.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mechóac an</hi> Out-ſmooths Latin, as Fame ſays:</l>
               <l>The Fiction ſure is ſmoother then the Phraſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="326">
               <head>326.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Latin</hi> is <hi>Rhet'rique; Rhet'rique's Muſique</hi> too:</l>
               <l>It does the Eare, by Art of Leaſure, woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="327">
               <head>327.</head>
               <l>All Art is <hi>Logique:</hi> in All 't is th' Immixt</l>
               <l>Cement: Reaſon in Man is not more Fix'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="328">
               <head>328.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Logique</hi> Defines, Divides, Collects; and Can</l>
               <l>Clear Fallacy. It is the Man of Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="329">
               <head>329.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Logique,</hi> they ſay, is glad to goe on foot:</l>
               <l>It treads ſure ground then; els it could not doe't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="330">
               <head>330.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> a <hi>Logique</hi>-Pope, who 'll ſay,</l>
               <l>Was Poore? Popes have Sixe thouſand pound a day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58688:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58688:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58688:26"/>
            <lg n="331">
               <head>331.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Suicet's</hi> Old Subtil'ties did fall to Banding</l>
               <l>With's Yong: His Witt grew paſt his underſtanding.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="332">
               <head>332.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Witt</hi> by it ſelfe and Language is ſtill ſhow'n;</l>
               <l>Yet without Pride: It can not els bee know'n.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="333">
               <head>333.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Demosihenes</hi> did Reine th' <hi>Athenian's</hi> neck:</l>
               <l>His Eloquence, though it could ſpurre, could Check!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="334">
               <head>334.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Tully</hi> ſee how high <hi>Rhet'rique</hi> can grow:</l>
               <l>Hee was <hi>Rome's Tiber,</hi> when 't does Over-flow!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="335">
               <head>335.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's</hi> High Witt, <hi>Porcius Latro,</hi> no man Can</l>
               <l>With higheſt Witt Out-ſpeake, or ſpeake the Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="336">
               <head>336.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quintilian's Bees</hi> ſuch Hony have brought home;</l>
               <l>Who would not long to taſt ſo ſweet a Combe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="337">
               <head>337.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tyre</hi> calls Choiſe <hi>Maximus</hi> Hers: Indeed, the Man</l>
               <l>Is Milke and Hony; a meere <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="338">
               <head>338.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poetry</hi> is Witt 's Spring-Tide, On it rowles;</l>
               <l>And what it meetes, Surmounts, or els Controules.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="339">
               <head>339.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mer's</hi> th' <hi>Atlantique</hi> Ocean, wherein brave</l>
               <l>Nature expatiates in Voluminous wave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="340">
               <head>340.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o,</hi> though ſome may ſeeme of higher ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Thy blood flowes Rightly in thy Happy Veine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58688:26"/>
            <lg n="341">
               <head>341.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucan,</hi> thy Age was leſſe, then thy Great Story:</l>
               <l>But thy Great Witt has Doubled Age with Glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="342">
               <head>342.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Statius</hi> his Witt and Language is ſo brave;</l>
               <l>Hee's in his Witts, and yet may ſeeme to Rave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="343">
               <head>343.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Statius</hi> makes <hi>Capaneus</hi> ſo fierce a Wonder,</l>
               <l>As if hee durſt ſtand to Conteſt with Thunder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="344">
               <head>344.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Martiall,</hi> th' art a ſure Mark's-man; what thy Dart</l>
               <l>Of Witt Aimes at, it Hitts, and makes it Start.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="345">
               <head>345.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vid</hi> was baniſh'd <hi>Rome:</hi> 't had been more fit,</l>
               <l>Wantonneſſe had been baniſhd from his Witt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="346">
               <head>346.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Claudian</hi> in too ſtraite Compaſſe does Ingage</l>
               <l>His <hi>Muſe:</hi> Hee is a Lion in a Cage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="347">
               <head>347.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Senecas</hi> in their Tragedies doe ſhow</l>
               <l>That Witt, which they to <hi>Spaine,</hi> not <hi>Greece,</hi> did owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="348">
               <head>348.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eemes <hi>Lycophron</hi> to write, or rather Thinke?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>writ</hi> hee with <hi>Caſſandra's</hi> Teares, white Inke?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="349">
               <head>349.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aliger</hi> rendred <hi>Lycophron</hi> in jeſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Verrian Latin,</hi> like his Senſe, hee's Dreſs'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="350">
               <head>350.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucretius,</hi> Nature's Favorite, excels;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> All's Truth; or, if not Too Much hee tells.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58688:27"/>
            <lg n="351">
               <head>351.</head>
               <l>How vainly at th' <hi>Olympique</hi> Games, Renowne</l>
               <l>Was ſought by Kings! <hi>Pindarus</hi> winnes the Crowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="352">
               <head>352.</head>
               <l>Though to the Grape <hi>Anacreon</hi> did incline,</l>
               <l>His Song is Above Grape; His Witt's his Wine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="353">
               <head>353.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horace,</hi> thy Art of <hi>Ode</hi> is choice: 't will Pleaſe</l>
               <l>Whiles Mankind ſhall delight in Song and Eaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="354">
               <head>354.</head>
               <l>Heav'n, Purgatory, Hell, were <hi>Dante's</hi> Three Themes.</l>
               <l>Two were Wiſe Melancholy; yet Extremes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="355">
               <head>355.</head>
               <l>What <hi>Petrach</hi> Loſt, hee kept: His <hi>Laura</hi> dies:</l>
               <l>Hee Loſt his Love, not Wit: his Wit was Wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="356">
               <head>356.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bartas,</hi> the Sunne makes Halfe the World ſtill Bright:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt Illuſtrate All both Day and Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="357">
               <head>357.</head>
               <l>Without <hi>Arithmetique</hi> wee can't know God:</l>
               <l>Wee muſt diſtinguiſh between Ev'n and Odd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="358">
               <head>358.</head>
               <l>Needs muſt wee know, what is One, Two and Three:</l>
               <l>How know wee els, what is a Trinity?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="359">
               <head>359.</head>
               <l>To <hi>Add, Subtract, Multiply</hi> and Divide,</l>
               <l>Does private Doubts, and publique too, Decide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="360">
               <head>360.</head>
               <l>To <hi>Number</hi> Rudely, is to doe it Ill:</l>
               <l>What muſt bee donne, who would not do<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c with Skill?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58688:27"/>
            <lg n="361">
               <head>361.</head>
               <l>Wee may have <hi>Napier's</hi> Bones, or Pratt's ſmall Table:</l>
               <l>Number and Art will thence us ſoone Inable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="362">
               <head>362.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Seav'nth</hi> Day and <hi>Ten</hi> Laws Number require:</l>
               <l>The Art then, as the Law, wee ſhould Deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="363">
               <head>363.</head>
               <l>If Holy <hi>Meditations</hi> you'd <hi>Rehearſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How will you find the Chapter and the Verſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="364">
               <head>364.</head>
               <l>Can wee forget how holy <hi>David</hi> prays,</l>
               <l>God would him reach th' <hi>Arithmetique</hi> of his Days?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="365">
               <head>365.</head>
               <l>Who takes the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Numbers</hi> in his hand,</l>
               <l>Without <hi>Arithmetique</hi> can he Underſtand?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="366">
               <head>366.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſique's</hi> Number in Sound: Inſtruments long</l>
               <l>Since, <hi>Jubal</hi> made; and <hi>Moſes</hi> had his Song.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="367">
               <head>367.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>David</hi> kept Number in his Dance: yet free</l>
               <l>His Voice and Joy were; as his Harpe would bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="368">
               <head>368.</head>
               <l>Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who bids our Joy breake-forth and ſing,</l>
               <l>Forbids not to the Voice to Adde the ſtring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="369">
               <head>369.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Boethius</hi>'s Learned <hi>Muſique</hi> and his Witty</l>
               <l>Philoſophy, are th' Happy Tune and Ditty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="370">
               <head>370.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſique</hi> ſo variouſly affects Men's Minds,</l>
               <l>The Art is not more wondrous, then the kinds!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58688:28"/>
            <lg n="371">
               <head>371.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Jonique's</hi> Quicke; <hi>Lydian,</hi> Sweete; <hi>Phrygian,</hi> Brave;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeölique's</hi> Soft; <hi>Mixt</hi> is All; <hi>Dorique's</hi> Grave!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="372">
               <head>372.</head>
               <l>If Lands were not Divided, Men would bee:</l>
               <l>The uſe then of <hi>Geometry</hi> wee ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="373">
               <head>373.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Joſhua</hi> into <hi>Canaan Iſrael</hi> brought,</l>
               <l>Meaſure kept peace: els all had come to nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="374">
               <head>374.</head>
               <l>Between Some Tribes <hi>Jordan</hi> became a Line:</l>
               <l>Diviſion 't was, which Tribe to Tribe did Joine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="375">
               <head>375.</head>
               <l>In the Beginning had not <hi>Paradiſe</hi> bound?</l>
               <l>It had layn open els, as common ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="376">
               <head>376.</head>
               <l>God meaſur'd <hi>Goſhen</hi> with a Line of Light;</l>
               <l>When 't was Divided from th' <hi>Aegyptian's</hi> Night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="377">
               <head>377.</head>
               <l>Meaſure can meaſure Light; Hence th' <hi>Optique</hi> Art;</l>
               <l>Miſtaken view has made an Army Start!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="378">
               <head>378.</head>
               <l>The Waters have ſeem'd blood by dusky light:</l>
               <l>The ſame ſeemes not the ſame by <hi>Different ſite.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="379">
               <head>379.</head>
               <l>To enlighten Light <hi>Vitellio</hi> does ſurpaſſe:</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>Reflected</hi> Light, <hi>Porta's</hi> a Glaſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="380">
               <head>380.</head>
               <l>By light Collected, <hi>Archimedes</hi> fir'd</l>
               <l>A fleete: Rare Art! But th' Artiſt's moſt admir'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58688:28"/>
            <lg n="381">
               <head>381.</head>
               <l>To know <hi>Refraction,</hi> needs a helpe but ſmall:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Aire</hi> and <hi>Water's</hi> Mathematical.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="382">
               <head>382.</head>
               <l>Meaſure and Number ſpread and Dreſſe the Sky:</l>
               <l>Diſtance and Starres teach us <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="383">
               <head>383.</head>
               <l>How the moiſt <hi>Pleiades,</hi> how <hi>Orion</hi> ſhines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> and Scripture too, <hi>Defines.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="384">
               <head>384.</head>
               <l>Without <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> Time knew no Dreſſe:</l>
               <l>The Markes were loſt: Story were Wilderneſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="385">
               <head>385.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scaliger</hi> would mend Time; <hi>Petavius</hi> would</l>
               <l>Mend his Amendment: Art by Art is School'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="386">
               <head>386.</head>
               <l>From <hi>Cenſorinus</hi> Diff'rent Yeares wee know;</l>
               <l>From <hi>Lalamantius,</hi> ſinces Doubts els might grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="387">
               <head>387.</head>
               <l>Some have thought <hi>Lilius's</hi> Account well donne:</l>
               <l>Their Diall's ſham'd by Clear <hi>Vieta's</hi> Sunne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="388">
               <head>388.</head>
               <l>From Earth and Heav'n <hi>Ptolomy</hi> wonne renowne:</l>
               <l>Deſerv'd not this No-king a ſtarry Crowne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="389">
               <head>389.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Copernicus</hi> does erre with great pretence</l>
               <l>Of Art: but <hi>Galilaus</hi> erres by ſenſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="390">
               <head>390.</head>
               <l>Who in his <hi>Eyes</hi> will place his <hi>Faith,</hi> may know,</l>
               <l>The Dev'l a lie may by Permiſſion ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58688:29"/>
            <lg n="391">
               <head>391.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Tycho Brahe</hi> Inſtruments did fit</l>
               <l>To Meaſure Heav'n; Siz'd by his worke, or Wit?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="392">
               <head>392.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Waggoner</hi> does the world's Chiefe Havens ſound:</l>
               <l>For Our Laſt Port, a ſurer Pilot's ſound!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="393">
               <head>393.</head>
               <l>To know the <hi>Loadſton's</hi> Myſteries and Law,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gilbert's</hi> the Loadſtone, that does All men Draw!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="394">
               <head>394.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lomazzo's</hi> a rich peece, which it ſelfe praiſes:</l>
               <l>Whiles Art by Light and ſhade, juſt wonder Raiſes!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="395">
               <head>395.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antiquities</hi> Refine Times from Fire and Flood:</l>
               <l>By <hi>Statues</hi> Time's Recall'd and Underſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="396">
               <head>396.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tais'ner</hi> ſhows Seventeen Hundred different Hands:</l>
               <l>By's Owne, Hee's Gypſy: Them who underſtands?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="397">
               <head>397.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Strabo,</hi> almoſt what Country, but th' haſt View'd it?</l>
               <l>Had'ſt been a Judge, Mankind would ſu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e have rued it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="398">
               <head>398.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Euclide</hi> and <hi>Rathbourne</hi> may lay-out a Bound:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vitruvian</hi> Art muſt <hi>Build</hi> upon the Ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="399">
               <head>399.</head>
               <l>Search wee the <hi>Mine</hi> for Gold, ſtraight make a Vau't</l>
               <l>Wee muſt; els quickely all will bee at ſau'ce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="400">
               <head>400.</head>
               <l>Come, Lets be Wiſe, and for the <hi>Arts</hi> Rejoice:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God's Word</hi> is Chiefe; yet Art too is God's Voice!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:29"/>
            <head>BOOK V. OF <hi>Philoſophers and Hiſtorians.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:30"/>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58688:30"/>
            <lg n="401">
               <head>401.</head>
               <l>High <hi>Metaphyſique,</hi> that on <hi>Horeb</hi> Dwelſt;</l>
               <l>Great Queen of Reaſon; Thou All Arts Excell'ſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="402">
               <head>402.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Religion,</hi> Thou on <hi>Sinai's</hi> Top doeſt ſit,</l>
               <l>Higher then <hi>Horeb;</hi> Empreſſe of All Wit!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="403">
               <head>403.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horeb</hi> was but Aſcent to <hi>Sinai</hi>'s Top:</l>
               <l>Bleſſings from <hi>Sinai</hi> may on <hi>Horeb</hi> droppe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="404">
               <head>404.</head>
               <l>Lets Teach what wee are Taught: not Inſpiration</l>
               <l>Wee now doe bring; but <hi>Nature's</hi> Demonſtration.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="405">
               <head>405.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reaſon</hi> Alone in Man High Truths can reach:</l>
               <l>Miſtaken Inſpiration can't ſo teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="406">
               <head>406.</head>
               <l>Before Time Somewhat Was, that could Make Time:</l>
               <l>That <hi>Being</hi> therefore muſt bee Moſt Sublime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="407">
               <head>407.</head>
               <l>That Being was but <hi>One:</hi> had it been Two,</l>
               <l>What One did, then his Equall might Undoe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="408">
               <head>408.</head>
               <l>The Firſt One muſt bee <hi>True;</hi> els 't is not One:</l>
               <l>What's Feign'd No Being has; and ſo is None.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="409">
               <head>409.</head>
               <l>What's True is Therefore <hi>Good:</hi> and thus wee know,</l>
               <l>All Goodneſſe els, muſt from This Goodneſſe flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="410">
               <head>410.</head>
               <l>The Firſt One, True, and good, by a clear Right</l>
               <l>Of Pow'r, as Being, muſt bee <hi>Infinite.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58688:31"/>
            <lg n="411">
               <head>411.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>How,</hi> what was Firſt, was Firſt, exceeds All wonder!</l>
               <l>Whiſper has more proportion unto Thunder!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="412">
               <head>412.</head>
               <l>What knowledge may of the Firſt Being bee,</l>
               <l>Nature firſt Learnes of what's <hi>Philoſophy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="413">
               <head>413.</head>
               <l>What's Good, wee ſoone Corrupt: thus with the <hi>Love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of Wiſdome,</hi> that's Philoſophy, it did prove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="414">
               <head>414.</head>
               <l>Some thought all <hi>Knowledge</hi> could but <hi>Probable</hi> bee:</l>
               <l>For them to <hi>Affrme'<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> was 't not Abſurdity?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="415">
               <head>415.</head>
               <l>Some thought <hi>No Knowledge</hi> Man could have at all:</l>
               <l>How <hi>knew they</hi> then, what they did <hi>Ignorance</hi> call?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="416">
               <head>416.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Doubtfull's</hi> Vex'd; the <hi>Ignorant</hi> is Mad!</l>
               <l>Hee that Attaines <hi>Sure</hi> Truth, is <hi>Surely</hi> Glad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="417">
               <head>417.</head>
               <l>An <hi>Ague</hi> ſome, <hi>Phyſitian's Bluſh</hi> doe name:</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Hidden Qualities</hi> the Philoſopher's ſhame?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="418">
               <head>418.</head>
               <l>From Diff'rent phanſies Diff'rent <hi>Sect<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ariſe:</l>
               <l>Thus Seeking Wiſdome ſome become unwiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="419">
               <head>419.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Sceptiques</hi> in uncertainties ſtill dwelt;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Stoiques</hi> Over-wiſe no paſſions felt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="420">
               <head>420.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> by his Father, was a <hi>Jew;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Circumcis'd: known and Taught by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> too!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58688:31"/>
            <lg n="421">
               <head>421.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> with the Gods did ſeigne to dwell;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lay</hi> hid, Return'd: and what had paſſ'd could tell!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="422">
               <head>422.</head>
               <l>Foole <hi>Man,</hi> that's <hi>his Owne Mocke!</hi> Whom pride makes quick</l>
               <l>To Hope, to get a God-head by a Tricke!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="423">
               <head>423.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> did eat nor Fleſh, nor Beanes:</l>
               <l>More does Hee, that Himſelfe from Himſelfe weanes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="424">
               <head>424.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> did love <hi>Muſique's</hi> ſweet Cloſe:</l>
               <l>Silence on's Scholers hee might well impoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="425">
               <head>425.</head>
               <l>Godhead and Witt <hi>Empedocles</hi> does lacke:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aetna</hi> holds Him; His Braſſe-ſlipper's caſt backe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="426">
               <head>426.</head>
               <l>From ſpeach with God <hi>Moſes</hi> his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace did ſhine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> having read <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſeem'd divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="427">
               <head>427.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plato's Ideas</hi> ſhap'd in Heav'n what's Heere:</l>
               <l>Did hee then ſee his owne <hi>Idea</hi> There?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="428">
               <head>428.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Stagirite,</hi> that in all Arts excell'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>new not Himſelfe, nor how the Ocean Swell'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="429">
               <head>429.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pinion's made Mens God; their Joy then ſure:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v'ry Philoſopher's Thus an <hi>Epicure.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="430">
               <head>430.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> did make Sleepe his Theme,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould hee have writt Waking or in a Dreame?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58688:32"/>
            <lg n="431">
               <head>431.</head>
               <l>For Skill i' th' Creatures <hi>Aldrovand's</hi> ſo Fam'd,</l>
               <l>You'd thinke 't were <hi>Adam,</hi> who the Creatures Nam'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="432">
               <head>432.</head>
               <l>Serpents, with <hi>Geſner,</hi> wee may ſafly view:</l>
               <l>Learning hee had; yet hee no Jugling knew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="433">
               <head>433.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salvian</hi> ſo preſents your various Fiſh,</l>
               <l>Hee may bee the <hi>Carthuſian's</hi> wiſeſt Diſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="434">
               <head>434.</head>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> wheres' ere hee grew,</l>
               <l>Was a rare Plant; Beſt Artiſts Him muſt view.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="435">
               <head>435.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aeſop</hi> ſaw Man oft become Beaſt: His wit</l>
               <l>By Beaſt then, to ſhew Man, might thinke it fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="436">
               <head>436.</head>
               <l>Kind <hi>Heraclitus</hi>'s Eyes with Teares ſtill ranne:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Democritus</hi> ſtill Laugh'd: Both make One Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="437">
               <head>437.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi>'s wiſdome did to Vertue tend:</l>
               <l>Hee did Himſelfe, that would all others, mend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="438">
               <head>438.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diogenes</hi> did Philoſophy O're-doe:</l>
               <l>Hee made Vertue Abſurd, and ſo ſcarce True.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="439">
               <head>439.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cebes</hi> wiſely inſtracts us in his Table:</l>
               <l>'Tis True Liſe; yet, like Life, lookes like a Fable.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="440">
               <head>440.</head>
               <l>A Good Example ſtill continues New:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cleanthes</hi>'s Tankerd is the Conduite too.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58688:32"/>
            <lg n="441">
               <head>441.</head>
               <l>To Man's ſhort life an Memory Thou doeſt ſize</l>
               <l>Thy worke, Good <hi>Epictetus:</hi> Brieſe and wiſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="442">
               <head>442.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi>'s a rare Surgeon; Hee Inures</l>
               <l>His hand to Gentleneſſe; pleaſes and Cures.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="443">
               <head>443.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi>'s perſevering Wit was Good,</l>
               <l>Till from his Open'd Veines flow'd Lines of Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="444">
               <head>444.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Moraliſt</hi> with skill ſcarce more profound</l>
               <l>Dreſſes the Mind, then Others dreſſe the Ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="445">
               <head>445.</head>
               <l>Contented <hi>Houſe-hold-Art</hi> cares not to Roame</l>
               <l>Abroad; 't is its Owne Happy World at Home.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="446">
               <head>446.</head>
               <l>How prudent <hi>Heſiod</hi> Laws of plow rehearſes,</l>
               <l>Breaking the Mould with a Glad Teeme of Verſes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="447">
               <head>447.</head>
               <l>How <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> does the Bee home lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>den bring</l>
               <l>With Hony? Hee's a Bee without a ſting.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="448">
               <head>448.</head>
               <l>How <hi>Varro</hi> does both Hen and Neſt prepare?</l>
               <l>The Chick's Halfe-hatch'd, by his fine Wit and Care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="449">
               <head>449.</head>
               <l>For <hi>Farmer</hi>'s Life Quaint <hi>Tuſſer</hi> All containes:</l>
               <l>The Wains, the Chains, the Swains, the Pains, the Gaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="450">
               <head>450.</head>
               <l>For Village-<hi>Lord,</hi> Brave <hi>Hereſha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> does marke</l>
               <l>What's Worth: Hee's a <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah</hi> in his Arke<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58688:33"/>
            <lg n="451">
               <head>451.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Italian's La Leſina</hi> ſhows, what ought</l>
               <l>In Curious Thrift bee ſav'd. Wee'll ſave a Thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="452">
               <head>452.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philoſophy</hi> is Humble, like the Eye:</l>
               <l>On Earth it Dwells; and yet ſurveys the Sky.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="453">
               <head>453.</head>
               <l>See <hi>Story,</hi> Life's Example; how it ſpreads</l>
               <l>A Patterne; in which out man All men reads.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="454">
               <head>454.</head>
               <l>Where <hi>Moſes</hi> his High Hiſtory began,</l>
               <l>Who knows? Was <hi>Sinai's</hi> Top his <hi>Vatican?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="455">
               <head>455.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> is Text; <hi>Joſephus</hi> is Tradition:</l>
               <l>Him our Faith reads; This read wee with ſuſpicion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="456">
               <head>456.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> is a World, part Truth, part Fable:</l>
               <l>To know <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are Truths yet, wee 're by Him more able.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="457">
               <head>457.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> is Hiſtory's Freſh Youth:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thucidides</hi> is Judgement, Age and Truth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="458">
               <head>458.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> is Gold of a Rich Veine:</l>
               <l>Thucydides no Melting needs! Pure <hi>Graine!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="459">
               <head>459.</head>
               <l>Story ſuppoſes Rule; Then patterne Finds:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Xenophon</hi> yet to Rule hiS <hi>Cyrus</hi> Winds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="460">
               <head>460.</head>
               <l>Philoſopher, Hiſtorian, Warriour too,</l>
               <l>Who <hi>Xenophon</hi> inſtyles, ſpeakes but-his Due.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58688:33"/>
            <lg n="461">
               <head>461.</head>
               <l>Who can not Oſt ſweete <hi>Xenophon</hi> repeat,</l>
               <l>And ſee from <hi>Perſia</hi> his Admir'd Retreat?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="462">
               <head>462.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Polybius</hi> againſt <hi>Hannibal</hi> Counſaile gave:</l>
               <l>His pen preſents him yet profound and Brave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="463">
               <head>463.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Greece</hi> rais'd, <hi>Polybius,</hi> ſtatues to thy Glory:</l>
               <l>But thy moſt laſting ſtatue's thy Owne Story.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="464">
               <head>464.</head>
               <l>The Heathen World's Antiquities may know,</l>
               <l>They All to <hi>Sicilie's Diodorus</hi> Owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="465">
               <head>465.</head>
               <l>Thirty years toile it <hi>Diodorus</hi> coſt,</l>
               <l>That, in the World, the World might not bee Loſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="466">
               <head>466.</head>
               <l>Brave <hi>Saluſt,</hi> thy rare Witt and Pen ſo act,</l>
               <l>As if th' hadſt been with <hi>Catiline</hi> in his fact.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="467">
               <head>467.</head>
               <l>Choiſe <hi>Salust,</hi> Thou thy ſelfe can'ſt ſo Diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>Th' art <hi>Ingurth,</hi> Fierce; and <hi>Manſiniſſa,</hi> Wiſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="468">
               <head>468.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar's</hi> Memorials are Pure, Modeſt, Plane:</l>
               <l>Had's Life been ſuch, h' had ne're at home been ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="469">
               <head>469.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Halicarnaſſius</hi> did <hi>Dionyſius</hi> breed:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> had of Him, then Hee of <hi>Rome,</hi> more need.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="470">
               <head>470.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's</hi> old Rites <hi>Dionyſius</hi>'s Care has ſhow'n:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> now were els unto in ſelfe unknow'n.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58688:34"/>
            <lg n="471">
               <head>471.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Livie's Rome's</hi> Empire! Glorie's Ample Spheare!</l>
               <l>Senators, Gen'rals, Provinces are There!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="472">
               <head>472.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> with ſuch light abounds,</l>
               <l>Hee's a bright Set of pointed Diamonds!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="473">
               <head>473.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paterculus</hi> his Wit we muſt commend;</l>
               <l>Unleſſe where hee appeares an Over-friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="474">
               <head>474.</head>
               <l>Had <hi>Curtius</hi> march'd with <hi>Alexander,</hi> Word</l>
               <l>And Art had conquerd All without the Sword.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="475">
               <head>475.</head>
               <l>When whither'd <hi>Salem</hi> felt the wrath of God,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> was a bud on <hi>Aaron's</hi> rod.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="476">
               <head>476.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſephus,</hi> but where from the Text hee ſtrays,</l>
               <l>For JeW's Affaires allmoſt in all things Sways.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="477">
               <head>477.</head>
               <l>Story is Patterne: well Compar'd 'tis Double:</l>
               <l>Ours is the Gaine, <hi>Plutarch:</hi> The Taſke's thy Trouble.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="478">
               <head>478.</head>
               <l>Pcace; you ſhall ſtraight heare a Court-Whiſper: Thus</l>
               <l>To Liſten, may n't wee learn by <hi>Tacitus?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="479">
               <head>479.</head>
               <l>What Lucke thy Witt had, <hi>Tacitus,</hi> to marke</l>
               <l>Rare Secrets? had'ſt thou Catt's eyes in the Darke?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="480">
               <head>480.</head>
               <l>A Secretary <hi>Sueton</hi> was, and knew</l>
               <l>The Counſailes of th' Emp'rour, and th' Empreſſe too?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58688:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg n="481">
               <head>481.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sueton</hi> his Method does from <hi>Rhet'rique</hi> take:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> keepes the Order Time does make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="482">
               <head>482.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sueton</hi> and <hi>Tacitus</hi> too much did know;</l>
               <l>And, but that Shame's Heav'n's Vengeance, too much ſhow!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="483">
               <head>483.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſanias,</hi> choiſeſt Travailour, Thy Fields</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Greece:</hi> 'Tis Thine, what Rare it yields.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="484">
               <head>484.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Justin,</hi> whither thou doſt contract or Make,</l>
               <l>Wee 'll praiſe the for thy Owne and <hi>Trogus</hi> 's ſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="485">
               <head>485.</head>
               <l>Though thy Great work, <hi>Juſtin,</hi> about does rowle,</l>
               <l>Yet thy Great Wit does thy great worke Controwle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="486">
               <head>486.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Florus</hi> is <hi>Livie</hi>'s Margent; yet does Vie:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Liv<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>'s a Goodly ſtatue! <hi>Florus</hi> th' Eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="487">
               <head>487.</head>
               <l>Thought and Tongue by <hi>Herodian</hi> is refin'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Politian</hi> is his <hi>Mercury</hi> and Mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="488">
               <head>488.</head>
               <l>New <hi>Livie, Dion!</hi> Thou, whoſe Life was Story,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>halt by thy Pen Live with a Double Glory!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="489">
               <head>489.</head>
               <l>To Search <hi>Vopiſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> and ſome few, who writ</l>
               <l>Like Actions, <hi>Aeſop's</hi> cocke may reach us wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="490">
               <head>490.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wiſh <hi>Euſebius,</hi> when on thee I look<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Thou hadſt been the Beſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in thy book.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58688:35"/>
            <lg n="491">
               <head>491.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Marcelline</hi> Senſe, ſcarce Words, could well Command:</l>
               <l>Hee writte ſure with his Gauntlet on his hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="492">
               <head>492.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Severus,</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Florus,</hi> Other Men</l>
               <l>Whiles Thou ſo writ'ſt, thou merit'ſt Thy Owne Pen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="493">
               <head>493.</head>
               <l>Story of late from <hi>Tacitus</hi> takes life;</l>
               <l>Good ſtories of bad Actions now are rife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="494">
               <head>494.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guicciardine</hi> Drifts and Shifts of Crimes has Writt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cambden</hi> and <hi>Strada</hi> ſhow Wiſdome and Witt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="495">
               <head>495.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe's</hi> Intelligencer <hi>Thua<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> brings</l>
               <l>To light, the more Retir'd Affaires of Kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="496">
               <head>496.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Priorato's</hi> ſtory Warriours march:</l>
               <l>But due to Him is the Triumphal Arch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="497">
               <head>497.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venetian Paul's Trent</hi>-Columne Fix'd does ſtand:</l>
               <l>The neighbour <hi>Alpes</hi> are not a firmer Land!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="498">
               <head>498.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Centuries</hi> are Truth's <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulwarkes on a Rocke:</l>
               <l>The Winds, the Seas may beat: They'll ſtand the Shocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="499">
               <head>499.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> His <hi>Roma's</hi> ſtory does Indite:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Centuriſts</hi> doe the <hi>Church</hi>-ſtory write.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="500">
               <head>500.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baronius</hi>'s <hi>Pyramids</hi> Renowne do winne:</l>
               <l>Yet is there Embalm'd Rottenneſſe within!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:35"/>
            <head>BOOK VI. OF <hi>Phyſitians.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:36"/>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58688:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg n="501">
               <head>501.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HIppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> are renown'd,</l>
               <l>Though Health's a Riddle no where to be found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="502">
               <head>502.</head>
               <l>An <hi>Atome's</hi> Reſtleſſe; witneſſe the Sunne's beam:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Droppe</hi>'s ſtill Chang'd; though ſtill 't is the ſame ſtreame!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="503">
               <head>503.</head>
               <l>For Health to the Phyſitian all Men goe:</l>
               <l>Health yet, is 't the Phyſitian's Friend or Foe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="504">
               <head>504.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hippocrates</hi> with Art the World did fill:</l>
               <l>Yet his Pure <hi>Oath</hi>'s more Wonderous, then the Skill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="505">
               <head>505.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phyſitians</hi> are Halfe-Prieſts: if then Impure,</l>
               <l>Or Blabs they bee; they rather Wound then Cure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="506">
               <head>506.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phyſique</hi>'s as Old as Sinne: Indure</l>
               <l>Diſeaſe, ſince Nature can't, it ſtraight ſeekes Cure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="507">
               <head>507.</head>
               <l>All Ages have their Helpe: <hi>Diet</hi> is Art:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Polybus,</hi> Nature's Scholar, taught this part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="508">
               <head>508.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hyſsop</hi> is purging; purging makes Man New:</l>
               <l>'T was well then <hi>Solomon</hi> the <hi>Herbal</hi> knew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="509">
               <head>509.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diocles</hi> both Phyſitian was, and ſure</l>
               <l>Phyſique! Fore ſhews Diſeaſe and preſent Cure!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="510">
               <head>510.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mithridate</hi> his owne Antidote became:</l>
               <l>That was Right king-craft! who els claimes That Fame?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58688:37"/>
            <lg n="511">
               <head>511.</head>
               <l>Choiſe <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> makes Man ſo wary,</l>
               <l>Hee may become his own Apothecary.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="512">
               <head>512.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Archigenes</hi> his Witt the Spunge does Squeeſe:</l>
               <l>Thought hee upon his Patient and his Fees?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="513">
               <head>513.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Apicius</hi>'s Cookery was a fullſome <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oile:</l>
               <l>Wee ſcarce preſcribe Salt, more then Hee does Oile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="514">
               <head>514.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Celſus</hi> is Art and Elegance: it were</l>
               <l>A Curious Art, to cure men by the Eare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="515">
               <head>515.</head>
               <l>Brave <hi>Oribaſius</hi> did with skill abound?</l>
               <l>For wounded <hi>Julian</hi> yet what skill was found?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="516">
               <head>516.</head>
               <l>To thinke the Bodie's Temperament does Guide</l>
               <l>The Soule, Great Sinners are on <hi>Galen's</hi> ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="517">
               <head>517.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> is Man: his workes the Bodies Frame:</l>
               <l>Their Number and perfection all praiſe claime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="518">
               <head>518.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> did live, as Some ſay, Seav'n ſcore years;</l>
               <l>A rare Phyſitian ſure them; it appears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="519">
               <head>519.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhazes</hi> for learned practice is a new</l>
               <l>And clear <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="520">
               <head>520.</head>
               <l>At ten years old <hi>Avicen's</hi> Zeale and Art</l>
               <l>Vied: H' had allmoſt All th' <hi>Alcoran</hi> then by Heart!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58688:37"/>
            <lg n="521">
               <head>521.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Avicen</hi> writes of <hi>Cordials;</hi> with the reſt</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et numbers not Himſelfe, though farre the Beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="522">
               <head>522.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Avicen's Canticles</hi> briefly renew</l>
               <l>Memory: <hi>Canon</hi> th' are, and Cordials too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="523">
               <head>523.</head>
               <l>To Make thy <hi>Canons, Avicen,</hi> which Containe</l>
               <l>All Art of Health, thy <hi>Canon</hi> was thy Braine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="524">
               <head>524.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſhius</hi> ſoiles <hi>Avicen,</hi> Phyſitian's Mirroir;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee brake before Threeſcore: That was an Error.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="525">
               <head>525.</head>
               <l>Who th' Aphoriſmes wants, wants Art and Eaſe:</l>
               <l>To want rare <hi>Faventinus</hi> is Diſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="526">
               <head>526.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maſſaria,</hi> had thy Care and Judgement gone</l>
               <l>Through All thy Art, wee had then All in One</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="527">
               <head>527.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſavol's</hi> th' Apothecary's Commiſſion:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſavol</hi> is the Rareſt Compoſition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="528">
               <head>528.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ancient</hi> times their <hi>Phyſique-Rules</hi> were True:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Theſe, Truth's ſo Refin'd, that Truth ſeemes New.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="529">
               <head>529.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugenius</hi> dares <hi>Maſſaria</hi> to refute:</l>
               <l>Witt againſt Witt is ſtill in glad Diſpute.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="530">
               <head>530.</head>
               <l>Accurate <hi>Argenterius</hi> will not reſt</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Old Truths: Hee <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll conſult with his Owne breaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58688:38"/>
            <lg n="531">
               <head>531.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Suchten</hi> your Antimony does cry-up;</l>
               <l>By Art and Hope now Form'd into a Cup.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="532">
               <head>532.</head>
               <l>Anatomy and Surgery doe raiſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fallopius</hi>'s Name: from Quicke and Dead h' has Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="533">
               <head>533.</head>
               <l>The learned <hi>Wecker's</hi> books <hi>Secrets</hi> Unfold:</l>
               <l>If ſo, Secrets they are but till they're told.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="534">
               <head>534.</head>
               <l>Experience has taught Cures: but who is 't knows</l>
               <l>The true Diſeaſe? This <hi>Rondeletius</hi> ſhows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="535">
               <head>535.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Montanus,</hi> though't ſeemes Paradoxe, does hold</l>
               <l>And prove, Diſtill'd, or Hot Waters, are All Cold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="536">
               <head>536.</head>
               <l>A Golden Tooth grew in a Child Though All,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ruland,</hi> admire; was Nature Chymical?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="537">
               <head>537.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercurialis</hi>'s Praiſe and Worth mount high;</l>
               <l>Yet in his Ointment may bee found a Fly!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="538">
               <head>538.</head>
               <l>Kind <hi>Montagnana,</hi> though on Land, does ſhow,</l>
               <l>How they are Orderd, that by Sea doe goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="539">
               <head>539.</head>
               <l>Bright <hi>Capivacci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> praiſing Thee wee 've donne:</l>
               <l>Is 't Art to hold a Candle to the Sunne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="540">
               <head>540.</head>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Fracaſtorius,</hi> thou waſt double bleſt:</l>
               <l>Thy Muſe, or Phyſique; who knows which is beſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58688:38"/>
            <lg n="541">
               <head>541.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dutch Æſculapius, Paracelſus,</hi> Dar'ſt</l>
               <l>By Art Frame Man; and with God's Worke Compar'ſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="542">
               <head>542.</head>
               <l>Would Nature ſeeme to make Old <hi>Galen</hi> New?</l>
               <l>Of Great <hi>Forestus</hi> it may ſeeme but True.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="543">
               <head>543.</head>
               <l>Whiles with Courteous <hi>Fernelius</hi> wee but Talke,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto his Art hee does us Gently walke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="544">
               <head>544.</head>
               <l>Quakes any at his Climacterical Year?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Codronchius</hi> will Rule him from his Fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="545">
               <head>545.</head>
               <l>From Phyſique did <hi>Wiërus</hi> runne to Evil?</l>
               <l>Shall wee begin in Art, and End in Devil?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="546">
               <head>546.</head>
               <l>Curious <hi>Mizaldus,</hi> writt hee Wrong or Right,</l>
               <l>Can not bee read, without a Choiſe Delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="547">
               <head>547.</head>
               <l>Sound <hi>Cordus,</hi> Thy Diſpenſatory teaches</l>
               <l>Such Art, as ſcarce Another Artiſt reaches.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="548">
               <head>548.</head>
               <l>Man's Heav'n and Earth: from Heav'n and Earth's his Cure:</l>
               <l>The Med'cine, Earth; the Time, <hi>Heav'n</hi> muſt Aſſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="549">
               <head>549.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maginus</hi>'s Art and Confidence will tell,</l>
               <l>How <hi>Phyſique</hi> with <hi>Aſtrology</hi> muſt dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="550">
               <head>550.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age,</hi> in his Calculated Tables, ſhows</l>
               <l>The Sicke Man's ſtate: His Death's Day too Hee knows!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:58688:39"/>
            <lg n="551">
               <head>551.</head>
               <l>A Queſtion't were decided not with eaſe,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Cluſius</hi> were Phyſitian, or Diſeaſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="552">
               <head>552.</head>
               <l>Ankle, Thigh, Arme and Belly-<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt, Foot ſpraind;</l>
               <l>Feaver, Stone, Dropſy, Coliques, <hi>Cluſius</hi> pain'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="553">
               <head>553.</head>
               <l>Some vaunt, they can all diff'rent <hi>Pulſes</hi> ſhow:</l>
               <l>Can phanſy? Senſe this Riddle ne're ſhall know.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="554">
               <head>554.</head>
               <l>Seaſons of th' year, five thouſand times though paſs'd,</l>
               <l>Only <hi>Catoſius</hi> does know now at laſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="555">
               <head>555.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sanctorius</hi> 's Phyſique is the Body and Scales:</l>
               <l>Weigh Right, and mend: Thanke thy ſelfe, if Health failes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="536">
               <head>536.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Obicius</hi> would <hi>Sanctorius</hi> 's Worke Demoliſh:</l>
               <l>Which coſt the Builder, Thirty years to poliſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="557">
               <head>557.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sanctorius,</hi> a Wiſe Builder, does with Care,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Statique</hi> Art, which hee well Rais'd, Repaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="558">
               <head>558.</head>
               <l>All <hi>Helmond</hi> writes, wee'll hope to ſay, Is Good;</l>
               <l>When wee ſhall underſtand, All's underſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="559">
               <head>559.</head>
               <l>Some ſecrets <hi>Helmond</hi> ſhows, which were more fit,</l>
               <l>If True, to bee conceald! Hence, Dangerous Wit!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="560">
               <head>560.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sennertus</hi> does all arguments purſue</l>
               <l>So well, Hee's Text and Commentary too.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58688:39"/>
            <lg n="561">
               <head>561.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venice,</hi> thy <hi>Trincavel</hi> yields thee a Name</l>
               <l>Beyond thy wedding Ring, though of great Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="562">
               <head>562.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſeeme foes,</l>
               <l>Learned <hi>Rorarius</hi> does the ſtrife Compoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="563">
               <head>563.</head>
               <l>Whiles great <hi>Hippocrates</hi> obtaines his Due,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hollerius</hi> ſhall bee Aphoriſme too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="564">
               <head>564.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crato,</hi> thy wiſe and plentiful Adviſe,</l>
               <l>Shows, thou gott'ſt ſame not from ſome New Diviſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="565">
               <head>565.</head>
               <l>Cauſes of ſodaine Death <hi>Terillus</hi> tells:</l>
               <l>Wiſdome, and prayer, ſometimes Death Repells.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="566">
               <head>566.</head>
               <l>The Quinteſſence of <hi>Man's Blood</hi> is rare Cure:</l>
               <l>The Quinteſſence of God and Man's moſt Sure!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="567">
               <head>567.</head>
               <l>A Child Cried in the wombe, <hi>Libavius</hi> ſays;</l>
               <l>Did hee begin his Griefes, before his Days?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="568">
               <head>568.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horſtius</hi> the Lover's pulſe by Art would find:</l>
               <l>Lets learne by Grace the pulſe of our Owne Mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="569">
               <head>569.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baldus</hi> man's mind will tell vi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wing his Nalles:</l>
               <l>Place the Commandements there, the Art ne're failes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="570">
               <head>570.</head>
               <l>From <hi>Curtius</hi> th' Art of Doſing let us learne:</l>
               <l>Strong Phyſique does not a weake mind concerne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:58688:40"/>
            <lg n="571">
               <head>571.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crinitus,</hi> Weigh'ſt Man's Heart? If Grace it fill,</l>
               <l>'Tis Light: If Empty 't is, then ſinke it will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="572">
               <head>572.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melampus</hi> by the Bodie's Moles would ſaigne</l>
               <l>Divine: by Inward Spots it were not Vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="573">
               <head>573.</head>
               <l>Anatomiſts Man's Body ſtill ſo View,</l>
               <l>As if this Art, when Man Dies, ſtill were New!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="574">
               <head>574.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurentius</hi> is th' Anatomiſt of his Art,</l>
               <l>Tranſcending in the Philoſophical part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="575">
               <head>575.</head>
               <l>New <hi>Remelinus</hi> takes off Man's firſt Skinne:</l>
               <l>So by Degrees unclothes each part within.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="576">
               <head>576.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Platerus</hi> Chippes-out Man, and ev'ry part</l>
               <l>Lays by it ſelfe, with ſpeciall Care and Art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="577">
               <head>577.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Veſalius</hi> does <hi>Fallopius</hi> diſſect:</l>
               <l>Anatomy by Anatomy is Check'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="478">
               <head>478.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bartholine</hi>'s Art and Eye are Quicke of ſight:</l>
               <l>His View's Review: hee does the Mind Invite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="579">
               <head>579.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſserius</hi> the Inſtruments of Senſe does ſhow:</l>
               <l>Our Senſes to His Reaſon This doe Owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="580">
               <head>580.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spigelius</hi> preſents Man, as at his Riſe:</l>
               <l>You'd thinke yee ſaw <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58688:40"/>
            <lg n="581">
               <head>581.</head>
               <l>Some the <hi>Anatomy</hi> of the <hi>Living</hi> write:</l>
               <l>Let th' Eye to its Owne Conſcience caſt its ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="582">
               <head>582.</head>
               <l>Has ev'ry ſore a Salve? <hi>Eraſtus</hi> then,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> proves the Man of Men!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="583">
               <head>583.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libavius</hi> the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Checke does ſleight:</l>
               <l>Shewing what Chymiſtry hee does count Right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="584">
               <head>584.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Libavius</hi> does your <hi>Crollian</hi> Magique try:</l>
               <l>And to the <hi>Roſeal Croſse</hi> has a like eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="585">
               <head>585.</head>
               <l>What's ſearching <hi>Lullus,</hi> the Philoſopher's Stone</l>
               <l>And <hi>Augurellus?</hi> Sure their Worth's All One!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="586">
               <head>586.</head>
               <l>Camphire-Oile, and ſome more, for Liquid Gold,</l>
               <l>With Gold-Duſt, paſſe; by <hi>Beguin</hi> yet contro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="587">
               <head>587.</head>
               <l>What's not perform'd by Nature, Art or Grace,</l>
               <l>Is Bad: where then ſhall <hi>Weapon-Salve</hi> find place?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="588">
               <head>588.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Taliacotius</hi> will a main'd face Cloſe</l>
               <l>To anothers fleſh, and thence make a new noſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="589">
               <head>589.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mathiolus</hi> and <hi>Lobel</hi> are choiſe plants:</l>
               <l>Without Them th' Herbal would confeſſe its wants.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="590">
               <head>590.</head>
               <l>If to the <hi>Spaw</hi> a journy thou wouldſt make,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ringus</hi> and <hi>Byetius</hi> with thee take.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58688:41"/>
            <lg n="591">
               <head>591.</head>
               <l>Who Travaile would by Sea, Waggon, Horſe, Foote;</l>
               <l>By <hi>Gratarol's</hi> Advice may better doc't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="592">
               <head>592.</head>
               <l>The Inſtruments of ſpeech in Beaſts, who reach?</l>
               <l>Rare <hi>Aqua-Pendens</hi> yet ev'n This dares Teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="593">
               <head>593.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quercetan</hi> does a learned Choiſe propoſe</l>
               <l>Of Meats: Hee does deſerve the Helpe hee ſhows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="594">
               <head>594.</head>
               <l>Old <hi>Trapezuntius</hi> did his Skill and Name</l>
               <l>Forget by Sickneſſe: <hi>Sickneſſe</hi> was His Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="595">
               <head>595.</head>
               <l>Drinke, fourteen Ounces daily, by juſt w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight,</l>
               <l>Bread and Meat Twelve! <hi>Cornar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> ſtrict Receite!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="596">
               <head>596.</head>
               <l>Who was the <hi>Beſt Phyſitian?</hi> ſhall wee ſay?</l>
               <l>Judge by ſucceſſe; It was <hi>Methuſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elah.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="597">
               <head>597.</head>
               <l>Allmoſt a Thouſand years <hi>Methuſhelah</hi> told:</l>
               <l>In God's Account hee was not One day Old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="598">
               <head>598.</head>
               <l>Twice as much <hi>Bread</hi> as Fleſh; Thriſe as much eat,</l>
               <l>As Fiſh: Once and a Halfe as Egge's Receite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="599">
               <head>599.</head>
               <l>The Lampe is <hi>Life:</hi> Man's Heat does daily dry</l>
               <l>His moiſture up; ſo that to Live's to Die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="600">
               <head>600.</head>
               <l>What's Life, Health, Phyſique? though one daily quaff'd</l>
               <l>With Thirſt and Phanſy, Doctor <hi>Antonie</hi>'s Draught!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:41"/>
            <head>BOOK VII. OF <hi>Lawiers.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:42"/>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58688:42"/>
            <lg n="601">
               <head>601.</head>
               <l>LEts keep <hi>Poſſeſſion;</hi> Cries the Law<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſtill?</l>
               <l>'T is well, if the Poſſeſſion proves not Ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="602">
               <head>602.</head>
               <l>Two things there are, the One of which is <hi>Mine:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Other e're I have 't, ſhall I call <hi>Thine!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="603">
               <head>603.</head>
               <l>Nature, art <hi>Cain?</hi> ſayſt thou at ev'ry ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Though Brother th' art, J'le have thy Goods or Li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="604">
               <head>604.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nature,</hi> although Corrupt, will have ſome <hi>Law;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſcape wrong, wee'll doe Right: Danger does Awe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="605">
               <head>605.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> is Law, Accuſer, Witneſſe True;</l>
               <l>Judge, Pris'ner, Jailour, Executioner too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="606">
               <head>606.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Heav'nly Angels</hi> know their Laws: without</l>
               <l>Order, Heav'n not Aſſembly were, but Rout.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="607">
               <head>607.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Dev'lls,</hi> that raiſe all ſtrife, ſtrife yet doe quell</l>
               <l>Amongſt themſelves: A Law there is in Hell!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="608">
               <head>608.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Relations</hi> muſt bee Own'd: Huſband and Wife;</l>
               <l>Father, Sonne; Maſter, Servant: Order's Life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="609">
               <head>609.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Head and Feet</hi> doe ſtill their Diſtance keep:</l>
               <l>The Natural Bodie's Politique, ev'n in Sleepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="610">
               <head>610.</head>
               <l>No Nation but does in it ſelfe keep Law:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cannibal's</hi> Owne Family ſcapes his Maw.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58688:43"/>
            <lg n="611">
               <head>611.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> more ſought for Glory, then for Blood:</l>
               <l>Much loſſe of This, Only with Juſtice, ſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="612">
               <head>612.</head>
               <l>What Blood the Body looſes, the <hi>Head</hi> feeles:</l>
               <l>There's quick Intelligence between Head and Heeles,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="613">
               <head>613.</head>
               <l>All Fault was Death with <hi>Draco:</hi> This Severe</l>
               <l>Decree was Life: Safety thus ſprung from Feare,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="614">
               <head>614.</head>
               <l>Fraile are Man's Laws; <hi>Iſrael's</hi> Laws are ſure:</l>
               <l>And only by Gods will Change or Indure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="615">
               <head>615.</head>
               <l>Of Heathen Laws the <hi>Roman</hi> bears the Name:</l>
               <l>In Diffrent Times yet, <hi>Roman's</hi> not the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="616">
               <head>616.</head>
               <l>Laws under <hi>Kings Rome</hi> had: <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pirius</hi>'s Name</l>
               <l>They beare, by Him Collected: Hee the Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="617">
               <head>617.</head>
               <l>When <hi>Tribunes</hi> Rul'd, the Law uncertaine grew:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Rome</hi> then thought, that All's not Beſt, that's New.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="618">
               <head>618.</head>
               <l>Troubles teach Witt: thus <hi>Rome</hi> did fetch from <hi>Greece</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laws in Ten Tables: 't was a Golden Fleece.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="619">
               <head>619.</head>
               <l>Ten Tables were at <hi>Rome</hi> to Twelve improv'd:</l>
               <l>To helpe what wanted, <hi>Rome</hi> it ſo behov'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="620">
               <head>620.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Epheſian Hermodorus,</hi> though Exil'd,</l>
               <l>The Authour is of <hi>Rome's</hi> Twelve Tables ſtyl'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:58688:43"/>
            <lg n="621">
               <head>621.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> muſt write of Law; it was Intended</l>
               <l>By Art and Blood: from <hi>Solon</hi> he deſcended.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="622">
               <head>622.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charondas</hi> 'gainſt his own Law, to his paine,</l>
               <l>Comes arm'd to Councell: by's Own ſword hee's ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="623">
               <head>623.</head>
               <l>What Various Laws <hi>Rome's</hi> Common-Wealth did know,</l>
               <l>Wee may: <hi>Zaſius</hi> ſhows Them: They him doe ſhow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="624">
               <head>624.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Papirian, Flavian, Aelian</hi> Law <hi>Rome knew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet wiſe <hi>Neceſſitie</hi> ſtill added New.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="625">
               <head>625.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's People</hi> from the Senator's did fall:</l>
               <l>Made Laws; and theſe <hi>The People's Law<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="626">
               <head>626.</head>
               <l>A People Needs a <hi>Senate:</hi> This does make</l>
               <l>Laws, which their Name doe, from the <hi>Senate,</hi> take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="627">
               <head>627.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's Prat<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had his <hi>Honorarious</hi> Law:</l>
               <l>At laſt the <hi>Conſul's</hi> Laws kept Alkin Awe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="628">
               <head>628.</head>
               <l>The Senate gave <hi>Naſica</hi> Houſe and Fame:</l>
               <l>For Law-Adviſe to Him the People came.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="629">
               <head>629.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Servius</hi> a famous Orator, by ſhame</l>
               <l>Wiſely provok'd, in Law got Skill and Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="530">
               <head>530.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Labeo</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> ſix Months ſpents ſix he Writ</l>
               <l>Retir'd: The Country was his Fame and Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:58688:44"/>
            <lg n="631">
               <head>631.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Trebati<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi>'s Skill; <hi>Caſcelius</hi>'s Eloquence;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ofilius</hi>'s Learning; was their Difference.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="632">
               <head>632.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Augustus</hi> did Himſelfe, whiles Law, advance:</l>
               <l>His Noble Art ſham'd Wrong and Ignorance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="633">
               <head>633.</head>
               <l>Man Rais'd Art; Art Man: Law did <hi>Lawiers</hi> reare:</l>
               <l>Some knights, ſome Senators, ſome <hi>Conſuls</hi> were.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="634">
               <head>634.</head>
               <l>By <hi>Caracalla</hi>'s Sword <hi>Papinian</hi> died:</l>
               <l>Hee ſcorn'd to Excuſe an Emp'rour Fratricide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="635">
               <head>635.</head>
               <l>Th' Imperial Laws, that lay before Disjoind,</l>
               <l>By wiſe <hi>Juſtinian</hi> in One <hi>Code</hi> wee find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="636">
               <head>636.</head>
               <l>What the <hi>Gregorian, Hermogenian</hi> Code,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Theodoſian</hi> had, <hi>Tribonian</hi> ſhow'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="637">
               <head>637.</head>
               <l>Prophane and Greedy though <hi>Tribonian</hi> were,</l>
               <l>Juſt and Free Art does his Name highly reare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="438">
               <head>438.</head>
               <l>Law includes Pow'r and Wiſdom: Theſe wee find,</l>
               <l>To have their Empire in <hi>Juſtinian's</hi> Mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="639">
               <head>639.</head>
               <l>The well Digeſted <hi>Pande<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts</hi> doe diſplay</l>
               <l>The Law: whiles what the wiſeſt <hi>Lawiers</hi> ſay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="640">
               <head>640.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Code</hi> has Pow'r: The <hi>Pandects</hi> have profound</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Theſe are the Law's ſure Depth and Ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58688:44"/>
            <lg n="641">
               <head>641.</head>
               <l>Law's <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> are the Youth of Law:</l>
               <l>Law's <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> doe keepe Age in Awe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="642">
               <head>642.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Novel</hi> Conſtitutions ſhow they are</l>
               <l>As a new <hi>Code,</hi> ſorm'd with <hi>Authentique</hi> Care.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="643">
               <head>643.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Feudal Cuſtomes</hi> may as <hi>Pandects</hi> bee:</l>
               <l>Their Right the Learned Lawiers make us ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="644">
               <head>644.</head>
               <l>Wit teaches Wit: Th' Imperial Artiſts ſhow</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi>'s <hi>Clergy,</hi> Wits which way they have to goe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="645">
               <head>645.</head>
               <l>Scholars Quicke Scholars are: <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great</l>
               <l>Sent-out commands, as Lofty as his Seat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="646">
               <head>646.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Canon</hi>-Law <hi>Gratian's Decree</hi> does reare.</l>
               <l>As the Church-<hi>Pandects,</hi> for a Thouſand year.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="647">
               <head>647.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth unto the Church firſt ſhow'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Decretal</hi> Conſtitutions <hi>Rome's Church-Code.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="648">
               <head>648.</head>
               <l>Th' Eight <hi>Boniface</hi> his Decretals does ſpread;</l>
               <l>By <hi>Dynus</hi>'s Art; which <hi>Roman</hi> Lawiers read.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="649">
               <head>649.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clemens</hi> the Fiſt His Decretals preſents:</l>
               <l>Ambitious Men ſucceed to proud Intents.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="650">
               <head>650.</head>
               <l>The Two-and-Twentith <hi>John</hi> does make new roome:</l>
               <l>Thus his <hi>Extravagant</hi> Conſtitutions come.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:58688:45"/>
            <lg n="651">
               <head>651.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's</hi> Church is now growne Empire: Has This <hi>Code?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like Reverence to the <hi>Decretals</hi> is ſhew'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="652">
               <head>652.</head>
               <l>Law <hi>Civil,</hi> has it <hi>Pandects?</hi> The <hi>Decree</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>as Pandects</hi> bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="653">
               <head>653.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> that doe their Taske purſue,</l>
               <l>Have now, by <hi>Lancelet, Institutions</hi> too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="654">
               <head>654.</head>
               <l>Has not the Church a ſurer Guide then Man?</l>
               <l>With <hi>Scripture</hi>-Canon ſure the Church began.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="655">
               <head>655.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scripture</hi>'s Church-<hi>Code:</hi> The firſt fow'r <hi>Councils</hi> know</l>
               <l>They're <hi>Pandects,</hi> which Themſelves to <hi>This Code</hi> owe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="656">
               <head>656.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Apoſtles Canons Zonaras</hi> explaines:</l>
               <l>To Prove them, then to Expound them, is more paines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="657">
               <head>657.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Gen'ral</hi> Church a <hi>Code</hi> had; th' <hi>African</hi> too <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>All that is Good in <hi>Gratian</hi> is not New.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="658">
               <head>658.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iſidore, Burchard, Ivo,</hi> Laws Collected,</l>
               <l>Which before <hi>Gratian,</hi> Church-Affaires directed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="659">
               <head>659.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Photius</hi> his <hi>Nomocanon</hi>'s a <hi>Greeke</hi> Light:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Balſamon</hi> ſtrives to make it ſhine more bright.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="660">
               <head>660.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lotharius</hi> and <hi>Bononia Irnerius</hi> Cheriſhd:</l>
               <l>By 's <hi>Interlinear Law-Gloſſe</hi> They too flouriſh'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58688:45"/>
            <lg n="661">
               <head>661.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Azo</hi>'s Induſtry was more then's part;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Summe</hi>'s the Summe of <hi>Azo</hi> and his Art.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="662">
               <head>662.</head>
               <l>But for <hi>Accurſius</hi> Law had had a Loſſe:</l>
               <l>Hee firſt, the whole Imperial Law did Gloſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="663">
               <head>663.</head>
               <l>Who th' Emp'rour's Right Oppos'd <hi>Vinea</hi> defied;</l>
               <l>Was hee not Wiſe? The Sword was on his ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="664">
               <head>664.</head>
               <l>Accurate <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> much does write:</l>
               <l>His Learned Summe't is that does Much Invite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="665">
               <head>665.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Law's Looking-Glaſſe</hi> the clear <hi>Durantes</hi> writ:</l>
               <l>A Glaſſe, in which you may behold his Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="666">
               <head>666.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Guido</hi> the <hi>Groſſe Clemens</hi> the Firſt became:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth Laws he knew; One Law hee Now might Frame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="667">
               <head>667.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bartolus</hi> Law, it ſelfe is enough Fear:</l>
               <l>Would'ſt thou both <hi>Pleader</hi> bee, and <hi>Judge</hi> Severe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="668">
               <head>668.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baldus</hi> with ſtudy, Age and Fame ev'n weari'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy in Saint <hi>Francis</hi> Habit would'ſt bee buri'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="669">
               <head>669.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Francis</hi> was, as Truth can <hi>Franc'is</hi> paint,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Baldus</hi> more Lawier was, then <hi>Francis</hi> Saint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="670">
               <head>670.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Panormitan</hi> in <hi>Baſil</hi> Counſil ſate</l>
               <l>When Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> had his Fate-well Date.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58688:46"/>
            <lg n="671">
               <head>671.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jaſon</hi> did the Whole Civil Law expound:</l>
               <l>Liv'd Long, and allmoſt fifty years Renown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="672">
               <head>672.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zaſius</hi> in Law did Reaſon moſt eſteeme:</l>
               <l>Of His Choiſe Thoughts hee ſhows us how to deeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="673">
               <head>673.</head>
               <l>For Practice in the Law <hi>Oldendorpe's</hi> Way,</l>
               <l>As Once With Him, with Others ſtill may Sway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="674">
               <head>674.</head>
               <l>Civil and Canon Law <hi>Oldendorpe's</hi> Care</l>
               <l>Does Sort: Knows the Compariſon Compare?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="675">
               <head>675.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Budaeus</hi>'s Choiſe and Learning give ſuch Light,</l>
               <l>Hee does New Pandects on the Pandects Write.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="676">
               <head>676.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alciat's</hi> Wit and Fame were <hi>Milan's</hi> Jewel:</l>
               <l>His Owne was his ſelected worke, His Duel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="677">
               <head>677.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cujacius,</hi> ſtill bee't Doubt, that neither boaſt,</l>
               <l>If Thou to Law, or Law to Thee, Owes moſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="678">
               <head>678.</head>
               <l>Rare <hi>Weſembecius</hi>'s Artificial Frame</l>
               <l>Of Law, which <hi>Tully</hi> wiſh'd, Raiſes his Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="679">
               <head>679.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> many a Wit have Vext:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mynſinger</hi> may bee Law without a Text.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="680">
               <head>680.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hotoman</hi>'s worth is by his writing's knowne:</l>
               <l>Could His Pen <hi>Junius Brutus</hi>'s writings Owne?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58688:46"/>
            <lg n="681">
               <head>681.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spaine</hi> on the Law Imperial will attend:</l>
               <l>Her <hi>Covarruvia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was her Pride and Friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="682">
               <head>682.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antonius Auguſtinus</hi> tries the Ground</l>
               <l>Of Law; Hee the Twelve Tables does expound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="683">
               <head>683.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calvin</hi>'s an Honeſt <hi>Lexicon:</hi> who feares</l>
               <l>To bee phraſe-jugled? Ev'ry word Hee Cleares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="684">
               <head>684.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Laws receive great praiſe</l>
               <l>From <hi>Leunclavius:</hi> Sh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'n't They His fame raiſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="685">
               <head>685.</head>
               <l>Exquiſite <hi>Gothofrede</hi> does ſo Tranſcend.</l>
               <l>The Law's perfection makes us fear's will End.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="686">
               <head>686.</head>
               <l>The brave <hi>Welſh Solon, Howell D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> much Glory</l>
               <l>Unjuſtly wants: His worth does Claime more Story.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="687">
               <head>687.</head>
               <l>By Law of <hi>Wales</hi> no Morgaging of Land</l>
               <l>Was good, unleſſe into a Kinſman's hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="688">
               <head>688.</head>
               <l>The Spring and Harveſt <hi>Welſh</hi> Vacations were:</l>
               <l>No Suite For Land the Judges Then might heare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="689">
               <head>689.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wales,</hi> at thy Judge's Right hand the Prieſt ſate;</l>
               <l>Who with the Judges did Deliberate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="690">
               <head>690.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Rhodian</hi> Laws ſhow <hi>Wellwood</hi>'s ſettled Wit:</l>
               <l>Though of the Sea, upon the Land he writ.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58688:47"/>
            <lg n="691">
               <head>691.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Grecian</hi> Armes and Tongue prov'd both but vaine:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Amphyctyones</hi> were the Wiſe Braine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="692">
               <head>692.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Linwood</hi> and <hi>Spelman</hi> Ancient wiſdome ſhow:</l>
               <l>Noveltie's Danger: with Time Errours grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="693">
               <head>693.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cowell,</hi> Thou haſt Order'd the Law: giv'n Light:</l>
               <l>Sunder'd what lay confus'd, and placed all right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="694">
               <head>694.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Littleton's</hi> Tenure's Ground: Free Land's rich mould:</l>
               <l>Fee-Taile is Gravel: Sand is Copy-hold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="695">
               <head>695.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lambard,</hi> Law's Antiquary, makes us ſee,</l>
               <l>By what High Courts Once were, what they ſhould bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="696">
               <head>696.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fulbecke</hi> Law Civil, Canon, Common, ſhows:</l>
               <l>Compares: Diſcovers, where they're Friends, where Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="697">
               <head>697.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fitſherbert,</hi> what in Year-bookes lay confus'd,</l>
               <l>Has wiſely ſav'd, from being more abus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="698">
               <head>698.</head>
               <l>What is <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law's Hope after Clear <hi>Brooke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deep <hi>Plowden,</hi> Quick-brain'd <hi>Dyer,</hi> Learned <hi>Cooke?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="699">
               <head>699.</head>
               <l>Beware the Sharke: if in Law's Sea wee fall,</l>
               <l>A limbe is loſt! If Loſt wee are not All.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="700">
               <head>700.</head>
               <l>Againſt Both Parts Law ſo does Oft prevaile,</l>
               <l>They're Swallow'd worſe, then <hi>Jonah</hi> by the Whale!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:47"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOK VIII. OF</hi> Kings and Other Worthies.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:48"/>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:58688:48"/>
            <lg n="701">
               <head>701.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſt Empiere</hi>'s Shuneſhine; Pow'r, that's got by wrong,</l>
               <l>Is Tempeſt: A fierce Tempeſt laſts nor Long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="702">
               <head>702.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> was not of his owne Kin the Firſt:</l>
               <l>The Chief he was: but what was worſe, the Worſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="703">
               <head>703.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Semiramis,</hi> did'ſt ill, to rule thy Sonne?</l>
               <l>Rule him whiles Child: when Man, His rule beguane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="704">
               <head>704.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> hard heart no ſhowres of grace obtaines:</l>
               <l>Now wee'll beleeve in <hi>Aegypt</hi> it ſcarce raines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="705">
               <head>705.</head>
               <l>Why did the <hi>Pharaohs</hi> raiſe ſuch maſſy Tombes?</l>
               <l>Fear'd they to come unto their Heavier Doomes?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="706">
               <head>706.</head>
               <l>Tremble fond <hi>Pyramids!</hi> The Laſt Thunder can</l>
               <l>Startle your Guilty <hi>Mumy</hi> into Man?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="707">
               <head>707.</head>
               <l>Vaine <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> when your Piles are hurl'd aſunder;</l>
               <l>Not They, your Folly 't is, ſhall prove the Wonder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="708">
               <head>708.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Nimrod's</hi> Tow'r and Pride th' <hi>Aegyptians</hi> led,</l>
               <l>Hee for the Living built; They for the Dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="709">
               <head>709.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> to Die in <hi>Nebo,</hi> did God ſend?</l>
               <l>Death was his Way: but Life't was, was his End.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="710">
               <head>710.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſhua,</hi> Thou waſt King' of th' Holy ſword:</l>
               <l>Was't double edg'd, like God's Victorious word?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:58688:49"/>
            <lg n="711">
               <head>711.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adonib<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zec</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut-off Thumbes and Toes:</l>
               <l>Cruelty's Folly! Fear'd hee Kicks and Blows?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="712">
               <head>712.</head>
               <l>Envio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Bloody <hi>Saul!</hi> Nothing could winne him.</l>
               <l>From his Fierce will: His worſt Wireh was within him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="713">
               <head>713.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>David</hi> was Moone; knew Increaſe, Full and Waine;</l>
               <l>Change too yet did in th' Heav'n of Grace remaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="714">
               <head>714.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solomon's</hi> Fame did from his Wiſdome riſe:</l>
               <l>His Wiſdome, nay His Folly, makes Us wiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="715">
               <head>715.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>David</hi> cut-off <hi>Saul's</hi> Skirt: The Ten Tribes doe</l>
               <l>Leave <hi>Rehoboam</hi> but a ſkirt or Two.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="716">
               <head>716.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> made Judges: ſome agree,</l>
               <l>The laſt great 'ſize ſhall in his Vally bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="717">
               <head>717.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> did himſelfe perplexe:</l>
               <l>This Diſtaffe-King could not himſelfe Unſex<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="718">
               <head>718.</head>
               <l>To Heav'n ſad <hi>Ezechia<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> prayer goes;</l>
               <l>Comes downe in Angel, and Deſtroys his Foes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="719">
               <head>719.</head>
               <l>Impious <hi>Sennacherib</hi> blaſphem'd his Maker:</l>
               <l>In his ſhed blood his Sonne with's Sonne's partaker.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="720">
               <head>720.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Manaſſes</hi> loſt a Crowne; The Lot of Many<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Againe receives it; ſcarce the Lot of any!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:58688:49"/>
            <lg n="721">
               <head>721.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſiah</hi> was Extremes; All Acclamation,</l>
               <l>His Paſſover! His Death, All Lamentation!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="722">
               <head>722.</head>
               <l>High <hi>Nebucha Inezzar</hi> a God began</l>
               <l>To Act: God made him Beaſt, to make him Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="723">
               <head>723.</head>
               <l>Wine in God's bowles <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> quaff'd in Flout:</l>
               <l>That night by th' Enimie's Sword His Blood flow'd-out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="724">
               <head>724.</head>
               <l>After Long Glory and its ſtrong deluſion,</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Felt and Saw his Owne Confuſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="725">
               <head>725.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Mede</hi> th' Aſſyrians Spoild; <hi>Perſians</hi> the <hi>Mede:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Captiv'd in Sinne, Sinners thus ſinners lead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="726">
               <head>726.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cyrus</hi> decreed God's Temple's Reparation:</l>
               <l>Happy it was, if 't was his Owne Foundation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="727">
               <head>727.</head>
               <l>A King and No King? Riddle, ſhall wee ſay?</l>
               <l>By <hi>Eſther's</hi> hand thus <hi>Mordecha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did ſway</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="728">
               <head>728.</head>
               <l>Happy <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> whiles with <hi>Esther</hi> join'd:</l>
               <l>Was't <hi>Jew</hi> and Gentile in one <hi>Chriſt</hi> refin'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="729">
               <head>729.</head>
               <l>Was <hi>Perſia</hi>'s Glory in <hi>Darius</hi> Ended?</l>
               <l>By his rare Patience was it not Extended?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="730">
               <head>730.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Darius</hi>'s Mother, Daughter, Wife (Love-ſnares)</l>
               <l>Were <hi>Alexander's</hi> Captives; Not Hee Theirs?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58688:50"/>
            <lg n="731">
               <head>731.</head>
               <l>Swift <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Land-flood! Such his Sway</l>
               <l>That his owne Fierceneſſe ſwept him ſoone away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="732">
               <head>732.</head>
               <l>Was <hi>Alexander</hi> more then To<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le and Sinne?</l>
               <l>Vexing Deſires, in Greatneſſe, ſtill Beginne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="733">
               <head>733.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Alexander</hi> Living is the Great:</l>
               <l>His Death, of Him and His was the Defeate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="734">
               <head>734.</head>
               <l>Abuſive pow'r <hi>Callisthenes</hi> Defac'd:</l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Alexander</hi> Himſelfe moſt diſgrac'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="735">
               <head>735.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> built his Horſe a Tombe:</l>
               <l>A poiſon'd Hooſe provided Him Like roome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="736">
               <head>736.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Macedonian</hi> Loſt the <hi>Aſian</hi> Throne:</l>
               <l>His Kin ſoone Loſt, or never Got, their Owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="737">
               <head>737.</head>
               <l>Who gripes too much caſts all upon the ground:</l>
               <l>Too great a <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> Greatneſſe does confound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="738">
               <head>738.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Wife 's and 's Children's blood</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſsander</hi>'s ſlipp'ry Throne no long time ſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="739">
               <head>739.</head>
               <l>In th' Eaſt the <hi>Grecian</hi>'s Pride firſt Rais'd its Creſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perſeus</hi> captiv'd by <hi>Rome</hi> droop'd in the Weſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="740">
               <head>740.</head>
               <l>Scripture is Library: <hi>Aegypt,</hi> thy King</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ptolemy Philadelph</hi> Thee Both did bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:58688:50"/>
            <lg n="741">
               <head>741.</head>
               <l>Seem'd <hi>Pompey Rome's</hi> Head? <hi>Aegypt</hi> was <hi>Rome's</hi> ſtore;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Pompey</hi> left his Coarſe on <hi>Aegypt's</hi> ſhoare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="742">
               <head>742.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antony</hi> was devour'd by <hi>Aegypt's</hi> guile:</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Cleopatra</hi> was the Crocodile!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="743">
               <head>743.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Anthiochus</hi> the Great, Fortune's ſhrine ſaigne</l>
               <l>Would ſpoile: By Fortune was't? There hee was ſlaine!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="744">
               <head>744.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Mad, God's Temple ſpoild:</l>
               <l>Was plag<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d; Griev'd; Died: 't was Gaine to bee thus ſoild.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="745">
               <head>745.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Macchabies,</hi> Apocryhal in Story,</l>
               <l>The World ſtrives yet to Canonize in Glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="746">
               <head>746.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mithridate</hi> forty years a warre maintaind</l>
               <l>With <hi>Rome:</hi> Hee Fought; hee Liv'd not; much leſſe Raign'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="747">
               <head>747.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mithridate</hi> ſlew Wife, Mother, Child; Remorſe</l>
               <l>Knew not! Some Wives, Hee Nature did Devores!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="748">
               <head>748.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> was <hi>Tigranes</hi> his laſt Overthrow:</l>
               <l>Active <hi>Tigranes</hi> was his Owne Firſt Foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="749">
               <head>749.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Herod,</hi> though Foxe, more Crafty was, then Wiſe:</l>
               <l>Hee's Foole, that acts crimes before Publique eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="750">
               <head>750.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caeſar</hi> was Warre: <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Peace: Impure</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tiberius</hi> was; <hi>Caligula</hi> paſt Cure.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:58688:51"/>
            <lg n="751">
               <head>751.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Claudius</hi> was Dotard; <hi>Nero</hi> beaſtly Mad:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Galba</hi> ſtale; <hi>Otho</hi> Trimme; <hi>Vitellius,</hi> Swad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="752">
               <head>752.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vespaſian</hi>'s Shrewd, and Baſe: <hi>Titus</hi> more Good</l>
               <l>Then Bad: <hi>Domitian</hi> is Pride, Luſt and Blood!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="753">
               <head>753.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nerva</hi>'s a Snuffe, that in the Socket blazes:</l>
               <l>And ſoone gooes-out, whiles the Eye upon it gazes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="754">
               <head>754.</head>
               <l>From <hi>Spaine</hi> to th' <hi>Indies Trajan</hi> did prevaile:</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and th' <hi>Indies Trajan</hi> yet did faile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="755">
               <head>755.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> was <hi>Mercury;</hi> a Mixture ſtrange</l>
               <l>Of Vice and Vertue; Of Great Art and Change!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="756">
               <head>756.</head>
               <l>Once <hi>Alexander</hi> could <hi>Diogenes</hi> bee:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Antonine,</hi> King and Stoique was in Thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="757">
               <head>757.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Severus</hi> might amongſt the Beſt ſhine bright.</l>
               <l>But that hee was th' Eclipſe of his Owne Light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="758">
               <head>758.</head>
               <l>Who does not <hi>Commodus</hi> and <hi>Baſſian</hi> Loath?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> was Himſelfe and Both!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="759">
               <head>759.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> ſtate <hi>Alexander</hi> O'rethrew:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's Alexander</hi> did Himſelfe ſubdue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="760">
               <head>760.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valerian</hi> Chriſtians vex'd: <hi>Sapores</hi> flayd him!</l>
               <l>How Cruelty helpes Juſtice? They Repaid him!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:58688:51"/>
            <lg n="761">
               <head>761.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurelian</hi> from <hi>Zenobia</hi> wonne ſome fame:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zenobia</hi>'s Worth did the fierce Conquerer came.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="762">
               <head>762.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> thou waſt the Spirits of Wine:</l>
               <l>Thou gav'ſt the World Tincture, or Taſt, Divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="763">
               <head>763.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julian</hi> revolts from Chriſt: yet can not ſtart</l>
               <l>From Death: was not Apoſtaſy the Dart?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="764">
               <head>764.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Raged, his Happy Shame</l>
               <l>Prov'd, Holy <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> His and Thy true Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="765">
               <head>765.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Attila's</hi> Pride and Futy did decline</l>
               <l>At once: Hee Liv'd in Blood, and Died in Wine!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="766">
               <head>766.</head>
               <l>Depos'd <hi>Glycerius</hi> is, by <hi>Nepos</hi>'s Will,</l>
               <l>Made Prelate; Had hee ſeeming Empire ſtill?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="767">
               <head>767.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guſtulus</hi> his Name was like his Throne:</l>
               <l>A little <hi>Caeſar</hi> Firſt; then Quickly None.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="768">
               <head>768.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtinian</hi> gave <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> Law:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Beliſarius</hi>'s Sword the World did Awe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="769">
               <head>769.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtinian, Beliſarius</hi> haſt Conremn'd?</l>
               <l>Hee was thy priſ'ner: Thou 't is art Condemn'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="770">
               <head>770.</head>
               <l>Many Warres caus'd <hi>Ravenna's Exarchate:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too many made Two hundred years its Date.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58688:52"/>
            <lg n="771">
               <head>771.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mauritius</hi> Captive blood would not redeeme;</l>
               <l>That ſhed; his owne did find as much eſteeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="772">
               <head>772.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Great his battles did record</l>
               <l>In blood: Hee writ them with the Spirit of Sword!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="773">
               <head>773.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Grecian</hi> Empire Conſtantine begunne:</l>
               <l>And in a <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſhall 't bee undonne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="774">
               <head>774.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Otho</hi> the Great did ſtoutly quell his foes:</l>
               <l>This Double <hi>Caeſar</hi> did a Pope depoſe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="775">
               <head>775.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hildebrand</hi> did <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth debaſe:</l>
               <l>But ſweet Revenge Raptur'd him from diſgrace!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="776">
               <head>776.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saladine</hi> to his grave bid his friends bear</l>
               <l>His ſpoiles of th' Eaſt, his Shirt upon a ſpeare!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="777">
               <head>777.</head>
               <l>For Seav'nty years <hi>Rome</hi> to Avignon fled:</l>
               <l>There <hi>Rome</hi> was, where <hi>Clemens</hi> the Fiſt, its Head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="778">
               <head>778.</head>
               <l>Queen <hi>Joane</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> ſo did act her Life,</l>
               <l>Shee ſeem'd as much an Hoſteſſe, as a Wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="779">
               <head>779.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>England's</hi> Fiſt <hi>Henry</hi> was a Sunne too ſoone</l>
               <l>Remov'd: Heav'n's Sunne's leſſe ſtrange: Ours ſet at Noone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="780">
               <head>780.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ziſca</hi> Alive his foes by Fight O'recome:</l>
               <l>When Dead, hee'd Conquer with his Skin made Drumme.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58688:52"/>
            <lg n="781">
               <head>781.</head>
               <l>Five hundred thouſand warriours fight with rage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Bajazet</hi> can't ſcape <hi>Tamerlan's</hi> Cage!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="782">
               <head>782.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Columbus</hi> was by his brave Spirit ſo hurl'd,</l>
               <l>Hee ſeem'd the Sea-Apoſtle of the World.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="783">
               <head>783.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> from the <hi>Moores</hi> wonne his Owne <hi>Spaine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From th' <hi>Indians,</hi> Gold: from Him They Heav'n ſhould gaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="784">
               <head>784.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Fiſt ſcorn'd Glory, Pleaſure, Pelſe:</l>
               <l>Turn'd Court-Monke and the Emp'rour of Himſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="785">
               <head>785.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Portugal</hi>'s Old Age was Spring:</l>
               <l>Hee Liv'd a Cardinal, and Died a King!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="786">
               <head>786.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry,</hi> Our Eight, few Painters have well made:</l>
               <l>Some give him too much Light, ſome too much ſhade<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="787">
               <head>787.</head>
               <l>Our <hi>Engliſh Mary</hi> in wrong Zeale's Deſire,</l>
               <l>Poore Chriſtians Burnd: The Counſaile was the Fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="788">
               <head>788.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was Temper'd to Inherit</l>
               <l>Her Grandſire's Wiſdome, and her Father's Spirit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="789">
               <head>789.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotland's</hi> Faire <hi>Mary</hi> Vext in Life and Story,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> has yet unridled to her Glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="790">
               <head>790.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drake</hi> in New <hi>Albion</hi> might a Crowne have worne;</l>
               <l>Wiſely Denied: Though't was not made of Thorne!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:58688:53"/>
            <lg n="791">
               <head>791.</head>
               <l>When Truth, Peace, Juſtice, Mercy, Arts, did flouriſh,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Henry,</hi> but <hi>James Beau-Clerke</hi> did them nouriſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="792">
               <head>792.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, the Firſt his people's Martyr!</l>
               <l>A Saint was Too, by right of th' Holy Charter!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="793">
               <head>793.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Body</hi> ſtrikes-off its Owne <hi>Head!</hi> Strange deed!</l>
               <l>The Head Cut-off, the Body Too Muſt bleed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="794">
               <head>794.</head>
               <l>King of Rare Lott and Vertue, <hi>Charl's</hi> the Firſt!</l>
               <l>The Beſt of Men! Judg'd, by the Worſt, the Worſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="795">
               <head>795.</head>
               <l>Beheaded <hi>England,</hi> ſtrange ſhall bee Thy Story:</l>
               <l>Revive in thy New <hi>Charl's,</hi> to a New Glory!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="796">
               <head>796.</head>
               <l>Our High-Noone Starre, <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> Shines!</l>
               <l>'T is bleſt Succeſſe, when Heaven with Earth Combines!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="797">
               <head>797.</head>
               <l>With Glitt'ring Swords, yet without ſhedding blood,</l>
               <l>See, Our <hi>Great Britan</hi> Comes! 'Tis <hi>Charles,</hi> the <hi>Good.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="798">
               <head>798.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yorke</hi> wing'd with Lightning, in a full carriere</l>
               <l>Flies-on, and reſpites not his Foe to Fear!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="799">
               <head>799.</head>
               <l>Kind <hi>Glo'ſter</hi> ſeing <hi>Charles</hi> Bleſt 'midſt juſt Deſires;</l>
               <l>To Heav'n, whence his Owne Graces came, Reti'res,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="800">
               <head>800.</head>
               <l>Kings Chooſe their friends: But <hi>Charles</hi> is ſuch Delight.</l>
               <l>Hee is the Heav'n's and <hi>England's</hi> Favorite!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="book">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:53"/>
            <head>BOOK IX. OF <hi>Polititians.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:54"/>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58688:54"/>
            <lg n="801">
               <head>801.</head>
               <l>PAint mee a <hi>Polititian</hi> with right foote</l>
               <l>Tip-toed, and Slily aiming for a ſhoote.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="802">
               <head>802.</head>
               <l>Your <hi>Politique,</hi> that will bee held moſt quaint,</l>
               <l>Muſt ſeeme, nay bee Beleev'd to bee a Saint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="803">
               <head>803.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> had Art, before he had great Pow'r:</l>
               <l>Hee built Himſelfe, before hee built his Tow't.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="804">
               <head>804.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Semiramis</hi> her Sexe and Plot did Hide:</l>
               <l>Scarce could ſhee els th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Empire guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="805">
               <head>805.</head>
               <l>Nature taught <hi>Jacob</hi> Policy: by which</l>
               <l>Hee made his Flock, and Him his Flock made Rich.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="806">
               <head>806.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shechem</hi> had Craft; but that on Luſt Heav'n Low'rs:</l>
               <l>Let's Marry; then all <hi>Jacob's</hi> Wealth is Ours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="807">
               <head>807.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f any a Shee-Politique would paint,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otiphar's</hi> Wiſe is Copy for ſuch Saint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="808">
               <head>808.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Midwives</hi> obtaine mercy, whiles they Muſe,</l>
               <l>Their Mercy to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Babes t' Excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="809">
               <head>809.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rahab</hi> on the houſe-top hid <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſpies:</l>
               <l>Heav'n ſaw't; though 't had not been ſo neere the Skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="810">
               <head>810.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ael's</hi> ſharpe Naile through <hi>Siſera's</hi> Temples went:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was the ſureſt naile in <hi>Ja<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58688:55"/>
            <lg n="811">
               <head>811.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abimelech</hi> his ſeav'nty brethren kill'd:</l>
               <l>By ſoulneſſe of his plot, his Plot hee ſpill'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="812">
               <head>812.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abſalon's</hi> Rage was more; <hi>Sampſon's</hi> more fit:</l>
               <l>Both did fire Corne: but <hi>Sampſon</hi> with Foxe-wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="813">
               <head>813.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philiſtines</hi> th' <hi>Iſraelite</hi> no Smith afford:</l>
               <l>Heav'n's plot! The Fooles doe fall by their Own ſword!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="814">
               <head>814.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Michal</hi> helpes <hi>David's</hi> flight, faigning him ſaint:</l>
               <l>Choiſe Wit! That makes an Image ſave a Saint!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="815">
               <head>815.</head>
               <l>Seemes <hi>David</hi> Mad? Feare 's Madneſſe: the Abuſe</l>
               <l>Of Sanctity and Reaſon needs Excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="816">
               <head>816.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>David's</hi> friends ſcape in a well O'reſpread with Meale:</l>
               <l>Them, not the Woman's Wit, it did conceale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="817">
               <head>817.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Achitophel</hi> did hang himſelfe; Wee 'll tell</l>
               <l>But Truth too; <hi>Huſhai</hi> hang'd <hi>Achitophel.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="818">
               <head>818.</head>
               <l>Had faire <hi>Bathſheba</hi> ne're been Too much ſeen,</l>
               <l>Faire though ſhee were, ſhee ne're had been a Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="819">
               <head>819.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bathſheba</hi>'s ſhape was her Firſt Wit: That Wit</l>
               <l>Court-taught, in <hi>David's</hi> Throne made <hi>Solomon</hi> ſit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="820">
               <head>820.</head>
               <l>A Crown to <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s a ſtrange thing;</l>
               <l>That would adore a Calſe to bee a King.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:58688:55"/>
            <lg n="821">
               <head>821.</head>
               <l>Proud <hi>Athalia</hi> a King's Wife had been:</l>
               <l>Rule ſhee will ſtill: Shee 'll Live or Die a Queen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="822">
               <head>822.</head>
               <l>By Night the <hi>Mede</hi> did <hi>Baltaſar</hi> beſet:</l>
               <l>By Night hee ſees, that can a Kingdome get.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="823">
               <head>823.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romulus</hi> gives <hi>Rome</hi> Bulke; <hi>Numa</hi> a Mind:</l>
               <l>Yet, though his Wit ſees, his Devotion's Blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="824">
               <head>824.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hannibal</hi> to his Gods <hi>Rome's</hi> Empire vows:</l>
               <l>Revenge for Sacrifice Heav'n n'ere allows.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="825">
               <head>825.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Vow would have fierce Vengeance throwne</l>
               <l>Upon <hi>Rome's</hi> head: it Falls upon his Owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="826">
               <head>826.</head>
               <l>Old <hi>Maſiniſsa</hi>'s Wiſdome's his beſt Pow'r:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee leagues with <hi>Rome; Rome</hi> els would all devoure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="827">
               <head>827.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugurth</hi>'s Truſt in a Father-in-law O're-ſways him:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Treachery, not Wit, <hi>Bocchus</hi> betrays him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="828">
               <head>828.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubtle, Stout, treacherous <hi>Jugurth,</hi> who can purge?</l>
               <l>Who can ſcape God? The <hi>Roman</hi> was his ſcourdge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="829">
               <head>829.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertorius</hi>'s Sword and Wit durſt try to doe</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s much as <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Numa</hi> too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="830">
               <head>830.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome greedy Swine will kill their Yong: Is 't true?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erod</hi> his Children kill'd: was This Hog Jew?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:58688:56"/>
            <lg n="831">
               <head>831.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sejanus,</hi> thy <hi>Tiberius</hi> was as Quick,</l>
               <l>As Old: at laſt hee Show'd his Maſter-Tricke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="832">
               <head>832.</head>
               <l>In Senate, Hopes <hi>Sejanus</hi> muſt adorne:</l>
               <l>Strange! Hee's Accus'd; Mas'd; Hal'd; in peeces torn!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="833">
               <head>833.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Jews</hi> kill Chriſt, to ſave their ſtate: profound</l>
               <l>Wit! But Humane! 'T was That did All confound!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="834">
               <head>834.</head>
               <l>At Once <hi>Rome</hi> Thirty Tyrants had: This Fits</l>
               <l>A Monſter: Many Heads! How many Wits?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="835">
               <head>835.</head>
               <l>Shrewd <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Empire Got: Deſign'd</l>
               <l>Partners! raign'd Long: then Rule and Wit Reſign'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="836">
               <head>836.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ruffinus</hi> Guards <hi>Arcadius;</hi> ſtill to raigne,</l>
               <l>Raiſes the <hi>Gothes</hi> to warre; His Plot's his Bane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="837">
               <head>837.</head>
               <l>Falſe <hi>Stilico</hi> brings down the <hi>Goth</hi> to <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Hope's his Throne: His Lot's worſe then a Tombe!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="838">
               <head>838.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eudoxia</hi> her Ambition ſhould exile,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> for all his holy toile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="839">
               <head>839.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phocas</hi> deſtroys <hi>Mauritius;</hi> who does ſtraine</l>
               <l>Conſcience for Glory, does miſtake his gaine!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="840">
               <head>840.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phocas</hi> by bold <hi>Heraclius</hi> 's ſword does fall:</l>
               <l>Great Craft and Pow'r are Much; yet are not All!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58688:56"/>
            <lg n="841">
               <head>841.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>France,</hi> whiles thy Kings grow ſlugges, <hi>Pipin</hi> intrudes:</l>
               <l>Keepes Court: the King was but the Moveable Goods!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="842">
               <head>842.</head>
               <l>The Second <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> as fame then ranne,</l>
               <l>Seem'd Witch: Indeed a Pope's a cunning Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="843">
               <head>843.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seav'nth many a Pope had made:</l>
               <l>At laſt hee became free of the ſame trade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="844">
               <head>844.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third by th' Painter's worke</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rodolfe</hi> betrayd to the Turke! The Pope 's more Turke!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="845">
               <head>845.</head>
               <l>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Pride on th' Emp'rour trod!</l>
               <l>Hee caſts contempt on Kings! A Vicar-God?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="846">
               <head>846.</head>
               <l>A foote-ſtoole-King may make Meere man ſo ſtout,</l>
               <l>The Swelling Pride may give a Pope the Gout!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="847">
               <head>847.</head>
               <l>Th' Eight <hi>Boniface</hi> was great, till hee ſeem'd great:</l>
               <l>H' had Wit to get, but not to keep, his Seat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="848">
               <head>848.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> de <hi>Medices,</hi> Judge of Strife unjuſt,</l>
               <l>Did in Himſelfe make friends Wiſdome and Luſt!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="849">
               <head>849.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſtruccius</hi> toild with Conqueſt to bee great,</l>
               <l>Looſes his Life and Plots with Cold and Heat!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="850">
               <head>850.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sforza</hi> a Duke and Traitour calls to his plot</l>
               <l>Helpe: His Helpe 's Ruine! Jaile and Shame 's his Lot!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:58688:57"/>
            <lg n="851">
               <head>851.</head>
               <l>Pope <hi>Borgias</hi> did a poiſned draught deſigne:</l>
               <l>Err'd hee in Faith? Erre hee did in the Wine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="852">
               <head>852.</head>
               <l>Had <hi>Borgias Peter's</hi> Key? Miſchief of Sinne!</l>
               <l>What is 't to Open Heav'n, and not Get-in?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="853">
               <head>853.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Borgias</hi> his Sonne <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſold to Evil:</l>
               <l>Proceeding hee took all Degrees of Devil?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="854">
               <head>854.</head>
               <l>Whiles Others Death Proud <hi>Caeſar Borgias</hi> ſought</l>
               <l>His Pois'nous Plot upon his Owne plot wrought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="855">
               <head>855.</head>
               <l>Miſtaken <hi>Borgias</hi> by High projects led,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> pull'd the houſe upon his head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="856">
               <head>856.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Macchiavell's</hi> working Mind ſtories compacts</l>
               <l>Into new Rules: Bold Judge of ſacred Acts!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="857">
               <head>857.</head>
               <l>Were <hi>Macchiavell's Prince,</hi> Satyre, paſſe it might</l>
               <l>As <hi>Florence</hi>-Libel; Witty, if not Right.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="858">
               <head>858.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Macchiavell's</hi> Wit nothing but Danger winnes,</l>
               <l>If't Undertakes the ſhame of Others Sinnes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="859">
               <head>859.</head>
               <l>In ſadneſſe <hi>Macchiavel</hi> thou didſt not well</l>
               <l>To helpe the World to runne faſter to Hell!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="860">
               <head>860.</head>
               <l>Who can 't Diſſemble, <hi>Lewis</hi> th' <hi>Eleav'nth</hi> ſaid,</l>
               <l>Can't Live: Craft ſhould not have this Craft betrayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58688:57"/>
            <lg n="861">
               <head>861.</head>
               <l>What Blood in <hi>Paris</hi>-ſlaughter, <hi>Guiſe,</hi> did'ſt ſpill?</l>
               <l>Thy Owne flow'd next: didſt thou not teach to kill?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="862">
               <head>862.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles Loraine</hi>'s Cardinal ſpeeches ſo fine</l>
               <l>Did make, which part hee tooke None could divine!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="863">
               <head>863.</head>
               <l>Such Secrets to the Eye <hi>Botero</hi> brings,</l>
               <l>Hee Audits the Eſtates of the World's Kings!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="864">
               <head>864.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the Third and <hi>Morone</hi> (they ſo compact)</l>
               <l>At <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Trent, Volpone</hi> and <hi>Moſca</hi> act.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="865">
               <head>865.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rome's conclave's Vulcan's</hi> Forge, where make they doe</l>
               <l>Inviſible nets for Bodies and Soules too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="866">
               <head>866.</head>
               <l>In th' Orbe of <hi>Belgique Spaine</hi> ſee th' Excellence:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Marg'ret</hi> was ſtarre; <hi>Granville</hi> th' intelligence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="867">
               <head>867.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spaine's</hi> Second <hi>Philip,</hi> Maſter of his Art,</l>
               <l>His Wit and Pow'r ſometimes ſeemes to Out-ſtart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="868">
               <head>868.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Indies, Philip,</hi> ſpread not like Thy roabe:</l>
               <l>Art thou the New Horizon to the Globe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="869">
               <head>869.</head>
               <l>How <hi>Philip</hi> in his Gallery views his Mappes!</l>
               <l>Conſults! Intents in Myſtery hee wrappes!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="870">
               <head>870.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſcurial</hi>'s <hi>Hammon</hi>'s Oracle in Sand:</l>
               <l>What's wondrous, <hi>Philip,</hi> does in Deſert ſtand!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:58688:58"/>
            <lg n="871">
               <head>871.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Perez</hi> flies <hi>Philip;</hi> Plots ſhews: reinvited</l>
               <l>By Hopes, relents: Abroad's Fear'd; At Home Sleighted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="872">
               <head>872.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philip,</hi> Day ends in Night: was <hi>Alva</hi> Lot,</l>
               <l>Or Choiſe? Neglect of <hi>Cales</hi> too, was't a blot?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="873">
               <head>873.</head>
               <l>'T was <hi>Gondomar's</hi> great Aime, nor did hee ceaſe</l>
               <l>In Project, to contrive all Chriſtians Peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="874">
               <head>874.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spalato</hi> moves, removes: H' had Time and Scope:</l>
               <l>At laſt hee leaves his Conſcience for his Hope.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="875">
               <head>875.</head>
               <l>Strange <hi>Campanella</hi> would beſtow on <hi>Spaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The World: but Hee'd bee Monarch of the Braine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="876">
               <head>876.</head>
               <l>Rare <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccaline,</hi> ſuch Policy th' haſt expreſs'd,</l>
               <l>That th' haſt Out-<hi>Macchiavell'd Machiavel in</hi> jeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="877">
               <head>877.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the Fift by his <hi>Venice</hi>-ſtrife Was ſham'd:</l>
               <l>By him his Cardinals, to his Gaine were tam'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="878">
               <head>878.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eight in Fear and Wit fell Sicke:</l>
               <l>Hopes bandy: Plots appear: Hee's well. A Tricke!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="879">
               <head>879.</head>
               <l>Thrice ten times <hi>Barnevelt</hi> from <hi>Holland</hi> went</l>
               <l>Embaſſadour; at laſt his Head they ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="880">
               <head>880.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Rhene-Elector</hi> loſt much by <hi>Bavare</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His friend: A kinder Cozen is not rare.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:58688:58"/>
            <lg n="881">
               <head>881.</head>
               <l>Nothing would <hi>Walſtein</hi> but a Crown content:</l>
               <l>His Life was but in Hope and Treaſon ſpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="882">
               <head>882.</head>
               <l>Had not the Empire's Troubles <hi>Spaine</hi> halfe-maimd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Richele<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> Wit had ne're been halfe ſo ſam'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="883">
               <head>883.</head>
               <l>Is <hi>Portugal</hi> a Cere-cloth on <hi>Spaine</hi>'s ſide!</l>
               <l>To Kill, or Vexe, or Cure, is it applied?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="884">
               <head>884.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>William</hi> the Firſt, whom Pride, Craft, Profit Sway'd,</l>
               <l>Did <hi>England,</hi> but his Conſcience firſt, Invade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="885">
               <head>885.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beau-Clerke</hi> a <hi>Saxon</hi> Lady weds: deep Art!</l>
               <l>The Head is <hi>Norman: Saxon</hi>'s now the Heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="886">
               <head>886.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Steph'n</hi> a Choiſe Courtier grows King: and wrong'd <hi>Maud</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enforc'd Conſents: Can forc'd Conſent mend fraud?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="887">
               <head>887.</head>
               <l>The Spirits are Blood: Wit moves in fineſt Spirits:</l>
               <l>By wit? by Blood, <hi>Steph'n</hi> thinks a Crowne hee merits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="888">
               <head>888.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>D'Or<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton,</hi> thy Oracle (was <hi>Delphian</hi> ſtranger?)</l>
               <l>Prompted bad <hi>Edward's</hi> death: yet thou ſcap'ſt danger!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="889">
               <head>889.</head>
               <l>How Craft does in the Cloſe it ſelfe oft mocke!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtimer</hi> Great, But <hi>Bad,</hi> ſtoopes to the blocke!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="890">
               <head>890.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bullingebrooke</hi>'s made a King: A great Pow'r choſe him:</l>
               <l>In Death Fear Checks him: would his Fear depoſe him?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58688:59"/>
            <lg n="891">
               <head>891.</head>
               <l>When the Sunne's Hid, yet the Eclipſe is ſeane:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Crooke-back</hi>'s Deeds Obſcur'd Heav'n: yet knowne th' have been.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="892">
               <head>892.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Morton</hi> fear'd his owne Head; yet ſo well us'd it,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s, and <hi>Crooke-backe</hi>'s Life, excus'd it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="893">
               <head>893.</head>
               <l>Does <hi>Warwick</hi>'s death our Wiſeſt <hi>Henry</hi> taxe!</l>
               <l>Crownes got by th' ſword, are oft kept by the Axe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="894">
               <head>894.</head>
               <l>Had <hi>Wolſey</hi> Faults? H' had worth! know Thou Thy Lot:</l>
               <l>Hee's Fame! Bee Thou content to bee Forgot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="895">
               <head>895.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gard'ner</hi> had Art, Zeale, Rigour, Craft profound:</l>
               <l>A Palſy-Prieſt, that was halfe-ſicke, halfe-ſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="896">
               <head>896.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Walſingham's</hi> Wit, Slander or <hi>Ghueſſe</hi> did ſay,</l>
               <l>Could through a Wall, Letter or Voice conveigh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="897">
               <head>897.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Raleigh,</hi> had thy brave Spirit been judg'd ſincere,</l>
               <l>As thy wit Sharpe, th' had'ſt ſcap'd both Axe and Fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="898">
               <head>898.</head>
               <l>The moſt ſwell'd <hi>Politique</hi>'s Vexation's Doubled,</l>
               <l>To thinke, His Glory muſt bee All Unbubled!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="899">
               <head>899.</head>
               <l>The Grief the <hi>Subtleſt Traitour</hi> can't Expel,</l>
               <l>Is't This, That hee can find no Crowne in Hell?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="900">
               <head>900.</head>
               <l>Ages to come ſhall bee Thy Juſt Adorer.</l>
               <l>Truly <hi>Wiſe Albemarle,</hi> England's Reſtorer!</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="book">
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:58688:59"/>
            <head>BOOK X. OF <hi>Divines.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:60"/>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58688:60"/>
            <lg n="901">
               <head>901.</head>
               <l>ALl things are <hi>Wonder</hi> ſince the World began:</l>
               <l>The World's a Riddle, and the Meaning's <hi>Man!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="902">
               <head>902.</head>
               <l>All Men are not Alike: Some can Diſcerne,</l>
               <l>And wiſely <hi>Teach</hi> Truth: Some can only Learne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="903">
               <head>903.</head>
               <l>Happy the Sheep are, that Enjoy freſh ſprings:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Happier</hi> is <hi>Hee,</hi> the Sheep that thither <hi>Brings.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="904">
               <head>904.</head>
               <l>To make the Sheep the Sheapheard is a Mocke:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Sheapheard</hi> then there muſt bee, as a Flock.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="905">
               <head>905.</head>
               <l>Wee're Kings and <hi>Prieſts;</hi> The King of Heav'n ſo makes us:</l>
               <l>Wee're yet but Kings, as Prieſts: Man els miſtakes us.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="906">
               <head>906.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kings</hi> wee are in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> Subject but to God:</l>
               <l>Not All men yet muſt ſcepter't: That were Odd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="907">
               <head>907.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Prieſts</hi> Men are heere in their <hi>Own Cloſets;</hi> where</l>
               <l>All for themſelves their Hearts and Hands muſt reare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="998">
               <head>998.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> may <hi>not Raigne, neither all Prieſt</hi> it may;</l>
               <l>The God of Wiſdome has giv'n no ſuch Sway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="909">
               <head>909.</head>
               <l>To a <hi>Kings Counſailes</hi> All are not admitted:</l>
               <l>By Wiſdome and High Favour Men are Fitted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="910">
               <head>910.</head>
               <l>The Meaneſt <hi>Sheapheard</hi> ſhould have Age and Skill:</l>
               <l>Els with the Flock it quickly will goe ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58688:61"/>
            <lg n="911">
               <head>911.</head>
               <l>One <hi>Timothy</hi> the Goſpel once did ſpread:</l>
               <l>But of an Age of <hi>Timothies</hi> wee ne're read.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="912">
               <head>912.</head>
               <l>A Taske and Honour 't is, but to Refine</l>
               <l>The Body: <hi>Soules</hi> to <hi>Cure</hi>'s a Taſke Divine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="913">
               <head>913.</head>
               <l>A ſurer Copy of <hi>Truth</hi>'s Worth's not had,</l>
               <l>Then by the view of <hi>Men</hi> ſome <hi>Good,</hi> ſome <hi>Bad.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="914">
               <head>914.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philo</hi> a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prieſt Chriſtians Commends:</l>
               <l>Shall Chriſtians bee worſe <hi>Jews</hi> to ſuch juſt friends?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="915">
               <head>915.</head>
               <l>To <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Laws <hi>Philo</hi> would adde a grace:</l>
               <l>Indeed hee takes the veile from <hi>Moſes</hi>'s face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="916">
               <head>916.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays, that Chriſt was more then Man;</l>
               <l>Roſe the Third day: Was Hee not Chriſtian!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="917">
               <head>917.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſephus</hi> did <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>'s Raigne foretel,</l>
               <l>In Propheſy, or Ghueſſe, hee did Excel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="918">
               <head>918.</head>
               <l>If to th' <hi>Apoſtles, Canons</hi> doe belong,</l>
               <l>The Queſtion'd Number does the Right ones wrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="919">
               <head>919.</head>
               <l>Growth's not the ſize of Grace: Judge not by th' Eye:</l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was but fow'r ſoote and a halfe high.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="920">
               <head>920.</head>
               <l>The Third Heav'n was beheld by Silent <hi>Paul:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Saint <hi>Denis</hi> ſaw it not: Yet would tell All!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:58688:61"/>
            <lg n="921">
               <head>921.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Copies did they Credit need.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vatican</hi> Manuſcripts ſmall ſaith would breed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="922">
               <head>922.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtin</hi> Philoſophy in Life profeſs'd:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Martyrdome a better hee Expreſs'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="923">
               <head>923.</head>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſoberly acute,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Valentinian</hi> Madneſſe did refute.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="924">
               <head>924.</head>
               <l>Though <hi>Irenzus</hi> Hereſy O'rethrew;</l>
               <l>In Phanſy yet hee <hi>Millenary</hi> grew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="925">
               <head>925.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tertullian's Mantle</hi> is a Mantle, which</l>
               <l>Shows his ſtricte Life; Halse hides his Wit, though Rich.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="926">
               <head>926.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi> Thy <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> are a Guide:</l>
               <l>Need'ſt Thou one? Is't from phanſy, or from Pride?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="927">
               <head>927.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clemens</hi> the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> needs muſt gaine yee,</l>
               <l>With His Choiſe ſtore; Hee is but One, yet Many.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="928">
               <head>928.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> is a Purer fire:</l>
               <l>Hee's Wit <hi>ad Octo:</hi> Would hee yet riſe higher?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="929">
               <head>929.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Julius Africanus</hi> writ a brief Story</l>
               <l>Of a long time: The Worke's Loſt, not the Glory.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="930">
               <head>930.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> without Death, by Art began</l>
               <l>To bee a Saint; by being not a Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58688:62"/>
            <lg n="931">
               <head>931.</head>
               <l>A Doubt it may bee, whither <hi>Origen</hi> writ</l>
               <l>With greater Errour, or <hi>with</hi> greater Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="932">
               <head>932.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Victor</hi> the Pope more Buſy was, then Wiſe:</l>
               <l>The Paſchal Quarrel hee did Overpriſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="933">
               <head>933.</head>
               <l>To Heav'n from Hell Chriſt's Way's without Compare:</l>
               <l>Magique and Martyrdome, <hi>Cyprian's</hi> Lot's <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>are!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="934">
               <head>934.</head>
               <l>Fond <hi>Manichie;</hi> what's Chief, only That's God?</l>
               <l>Two Chiefes there are not: what's Supreme, is Odd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="935">
               <head>935.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arnobius</hi> does with Learning and much Zeale</l>
               <l>Hate <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gan Rites, if not too much reveale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="936">
               <head>936.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> happy Eloquence diſplays:</l>
               <l>His Doctrine's not ſo happy, as his Phraſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="937">
               <head>937.</head>
               <l>Thou <hi>Epicycle</hi> of the Church <hi>Donatus,</hi> why</l>
               <l>Art not contented with the Common Sky?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="938">
               <head>938.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Donatus</hi> would his Church a new Arke make;</l>
               <l>When as 't is Flood, not Arke! A ſtrange Miſtake!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="939">
               <head>939.</head>
               <l>The Gyant <hi>Arius</hi> ſaigne to Heav'n would Climbe,</l>
               <l>To fight with God? Is hee not too Sublime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="940">
               <head>940.</head>
               <l>'T was Pitty. Arius did <hi>Euſebius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aint.</l>
               <l>Taking the Sonne of God but for a Saint.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58688:62"/>
            <lg n="941">
               <head>941.</head>
               <l>A Biſhop <hi>Athanaſius</hi> faign'd, whiles under</l>
               <l>The Age of Wit: Sport was the Type of Wonder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="942">
               <head>942.</head>
               <l>Moſt Chriſtian <hi>Athanaſius!</hi> Rare Projector</l>
               <l>Of a ſtranger ſame; that was his God's Protector!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="943">
               <head>943.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Nice<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Creed Chriſt's Godhead does profeſſe:</l>
               <l>Were hee a Saviour els? Sure hee were Leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="944">
               <head>944.</head>
               <l>Saint <hi>Hilary,</hi> who in High Languague rowl'd,</l>
               <l>Chriſtian and Biſhop's made, when hee is Old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="945">
               <head>945.</head>
               <l>Of Baptiſme could vaine <hi>Mac<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>donius</hi> boaſt,</l>
               <l>And for a Creature take the Holy Ghoſt?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="946">
               <head>946.</head>
               <l>Grave, Wiſe, Sweet <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d deſires,</l>
               <l>Was his Owne Mon<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt'ry, his Thoughts the Friers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="947">
               <head>947.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nyſſene,</hi> thy brother <hi>Baſil</hi> might bee ſame</l>
               <l>For both; but Thou too Liv'ſt by thy Owne Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="948">
               <head>948.</head>
               <l>High <hi>Nazianzene</hi> and ſta<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing! That 's thy D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</l>
               <l>Harke how it Thunders! And it Lighte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s too!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="949">
               <head>949.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cyprus,</hi> thy Wood does from Corruption ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e;</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Ephiph<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> from Hor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie's Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="950">
               <head>950.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> upon thy Infant-Lippes Bees ſate:</l>
               <l>Still on the Hony of thy Lippes All Waite.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:58688:63"/>
            <lg n="951">
               <head>951.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſtantinople-Fathers</hi> did Inherit</l>
               <l>God's Grace, whiles they Profeſs'd the Holy Spirit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="952">
               <head>952.</head>
               <l>True Muſique, <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> Thou waſt: The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pheare</l>
               <l>Was ſaign'd: Bee Thou Still Tongue, wee'll ſtill bee Eare</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="953">
               <head>953.</head>
               <l>Sharpe <hi>Jerom,</hi> to whoſe Critique Skill all ſeeke,</l>
               <l>Tutor'd th' Old Church in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>brew, Greek.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="954">
               <head>954.</head>
               <l>Great <hi>Auſtin!</hi> To bee Good, thou didſt not ſaint:</l>
               <l>Thy Youth was <hi>Auſtia:</hi> but thy Age was Saint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="955">
               <head>955.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auſtin,</hi> thou Chriſtian <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſame did'ſt winne</l>
               <l>From Monſters! Thou ſtalt weare the Lion's Skinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="956">
               <head>956.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Britaine</hi> firſt, <hi>Pel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gius,</hi> ſawiſt the Sky?</l>
               <l>Wee'll pray two, that in <hi>Britains</hi> thou maiſt Die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="957">
               <head>957.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seleucian Baſil,</hi> like ſtrong fire's thy ſoule:</l>
               <l>Whence ſtill doe mount Sounes of the Burning coule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="958">
               <head>958.</head>
               <l>Noble <hi>Syneſius,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licate as the Dove!</l>
               <l>Downe's not ſo So<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t: as Soft thou are as Love!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="959">
               <head>959.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salvian,</hi> art Over-righteous? Thy <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ierce Zeale,</l>
               <l>Wee Hope, miſtakes: thou would'ſt, whom thou would Heal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="960">
               <head>960.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cyryll</hi> his <hi>Alexandri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dorne,</l>
               <l>Whiles his Wit on Neſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> juſt Scorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:58688:63"/>
            <lg n="961">
               <head>961.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> from <hi>Cyril</hi> once diſſented:</l>
               <l>Hee had not els ſo lear<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edly r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pented.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="962">
               <head>962.</head>
               <l>Th' <hi>Epheſian</hi> Fathers did <hi>Neſtorius</hi> quell:</l>
               <l>Hee thought Two Perſons did in one Chriſt dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="963">
               <head>963.</head>
               <l>Two perſons can't make One: <hi>Two natures</hi> can</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One Perſon</hi> make: Thus is Chriſt God and Man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="964">
               <head>964.</head>
               <l>God is not Man; This would Confuſion make:</l>
               <l>But <hi>into God, God</hi> did the <hi>Manhood take.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="965">
               <head>965.</head>
               <l>Truth and Saint <hi>Austin <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſper</hi> did defend;</l>
               <l>A friend hee was to Truth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Truth's friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="966">
               <head>966.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vincentius</hi> Judge of trutly next to the Beſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Th' art Sentence, not Diſcourſe: Th' haſt all expreſs'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="967">
               <head>967.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> unarm'd did turne-back <hi>Attila</hi>'s Sword:</l>
               <l>And arm'd with Truth quell'd Hereſy wit<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s Word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="968">
               <head>968.</head>
               <l>Chriſt's Manhood <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>th'</hi> Abſurd denied:</l>
               <l>Wee His; if Manhood bee by Reaſon tried.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="969">
               <head>969.</head>
               <l>Chriſt if not God, From Sinne Can no man quit:</l>
               <l>By being <hi>Man,</hi> Chriſt to five Man, is Fitt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="970">
               <head>970.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sidonius</hi> his wit, Muſe and Honour claime</l>
               <l>Like-Right, to blazo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> happy Fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:58688:64"/>
            <lg n="971">
               <head>971.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chryſologus</hi> upon himſelfe did try</l>
               <l>Practice: His Wit and his Devotion vie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="972">
               <head>972.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> thy true: Luſtre <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'ere ſhall waine;</l>
               <l>That didſt Chriſt's Godhead and his Grace Maintaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="973">
               <head>973.</head>
               <l>Time's Date from <hi>Diocleſian</hi> once begunne:</l>
               <l>From Chriſt's Birth <hi>Dionyſius</hi> made it runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="974">
               <head>974.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Job</hi> had fow'r Counſailours: but his Fiſt Friend,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Gregory,</hi> does on us his Counſaile ſpend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="975">
               <head>975.</head>
               <l>Eve, <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Iſid<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re</hi> would know</l>
               <l>All things: Doe they in Heav'n None Here below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="976">
               <head>976.</head>
               <l>Poppy-braind <hi>Mahomet</hi> dream'd a Religion;</l>
               <l>H' had need to bragge, ſure, of his holy pidgeon!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="977">
               <head>977.</head>
               <l>Peruſe the Various Labours of Old <hi>Bede;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You'll muſe, whither hee did more Write, or Read.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="978">
               <head>978.</head>
               <l>Wrong'd <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſcens</hi> did looſe his hand<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> betwixt</l>
               <l>Errour and Truth he writ: the Man is Mixt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="979">
               <head>979.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Photius</hi> the Pope of <hi>Greece</hi> learnedly knowne</l>
               <l>By Others Workes, makes Their Workes Halfe his Owne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="980">
               <head>980.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> ſo happily imploi'd his thought,</l>
               <l>Hee ſcarce had time to thinke of what was nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:58688:64"/>
            <lg n="981">
               <head>981.</head>
               <l>Fable and Malice is a <hi>Rabbine</hi>'s Skill;</l>
               <l>Their Rites excepted: the Reſt th' expreſſe ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="982">
               <head>982.</head>
               <l>Of <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites <hi>Ben-maimon</hi> does write true:</l>
               <l>Happier <hi>Lyranus</hi> was a Chriſtian-<hi>Jew.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="983">
               <head>983.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Galily</hi>'s Glaſſe would in Heav'n find-out Ground:</l>
               <l>In high <hi>Aquinos</hi>'s Wit errour is ſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="984">
               <head>984.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotus</hi> oppos'd <hi>Aquinas</hi>'s Wit; nay more,</l>
               <l>Head<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a Sect: yet Died at Thirty ſow'r.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="985">
               <head>985.</head>
               <l>Many built <hi>Bable's</hi> Tow'r; but <hi>Nim<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d's</hi> Fame:</l>
               <l>Other mens Piles ſo <hi>raiſe T<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtatus</hi>'s Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="986">
               <head>986.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> Differd and Agreed:</l>
               <l>Their Difference has made them both worſe ſpeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="987">
               <head>987.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beza,</hi> though Critiques ſtill Thy Taſke purſue</l>
               <l>Thy Diligence and Copy will bee true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="988">
               <head>988.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Montanus</hi> in Tranſlating ſeldome trippes:</l>
               <l>Rare Man! In Fear yet the Lord's Prayer hee Clippes,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="989">
               <head>989.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> pleads for Truth with Reaſons fit:</l>
               <l>Againſt Truth hee brings Names and Seeming Wit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="990">
               <head>990.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Founder</hi> of th' <hi>Annels,</hi> whiles as partial blam'd,</l>
               <l>May <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'t thy worke bee <hi>Maſſa Corrupt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> Nam'd!</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:58688:65"/>
            <lg n="991">
               <head>991.</head>
               <l>Though Method, Clearneſſe, and Compleatneſſe, call</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valentia</hi> Happy; Hee writ ſince the Fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="992">
               <head>992.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vaſquez</hi> is a deep Pioner; his Vau't</l>
               <l>Hee makes with Art: yet ſometimes 't is at fau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="993">
               <head>993.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arez</hi> his Curious Webbe ſo fine does ſpinne;</l>
               <l>Ar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> makes it weake; and oft it proves too Thinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="994">
               <head>994.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cinus</hi> would an <hi>Archi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edes</hi> prove:</l>
               <l>Stepp'd from the Church, the Church he would remove.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="995">
               <head>995.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poſa</hi> his Creed, Pope and <hi>Aquinus</hi> ſleighted!</l>
               <l>In <hi>Spaine</hi> too! Hee was Over-Jeſuited!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="996">
               <head>996.</head>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Martyr<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſtout <hi>Cheminitius,</hi> and the Mild</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>taker,</hi> have Sathans Hopes much beguil'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="997">
               <head>997.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ier</hi> comes in the Beere: Hee ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ornes to yield;</l>
               <l>Conquers; and take the full ſpoile of the field.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="998">
               <head>998.</head>
               <l>Though ſome, of Earth j' th; <hi>Moone,</hi> doe vainly tell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elect</hi> Earth ſhall in Heav'n for ever dwell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="999">
               <head>999.</head>
               <l>A Thouſand Beauties <hi>Solomon</hi> injoi'd.</l>
               <l>Some will bee with theſe Thouſand Thoughts Imploy'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="1000">
               <head>1000.</head>
               <l>Father of Gifts, who to the Duſt did'ſt Give</l>
               <l>Life, ſay to theſe my Meditations, <hi>Live.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:58688:65"/>
            <head>Emendations.</head>
            <p>NUmb. 45. l. 1. r. cold is n. 60. l. 1. r. feares, n. 82. l. 2. r. Nature's Art. n. 119. l. 1. r. ſhrimp. n. 231. l. 2. r. <hi>Byſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</hi> n. 255. l. 1. r. ſhow'd. n. 265. l. 1. r. Globes. n. 273. l. 1. r. joint-meale. n. 320. l. 1. r. ſhows. n. 321. l. i. r. twenty-two. n. 439. l. 1. r. inſtructs. n. 441. l. 1. r. and. n. 470. l. 2. r. it. ſelfe. n. 483. l. 2. r. what ſo e're rare. n. 504. l. 2. r. hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſkill, n. 506. l. 1. r. Tamely indure n. 590. l. 2. r. <hi>Byetius.</hi> n. 625. l. 1. r. ſenators. n. 645. l. 1. r. reare; n. 745. l. 1. r. Apocryphal. n. 786. l. 1. r. eight. n. 819. l. 2. r. Court-taught. n. 876. l. 1. r. <hi>Bocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line.</hi> n. 886. l. 1. r. <hi>Maud.</hi> n. 888. l. 1. r. <hi>D'Orlton.</hi> l. 2. r. ſcap'dſt.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
